[BELL CHIMING]
[SQUEALING IN DISTANCE]
[SQUEALING CONTINUES
IN DISTANCE]
- Who's there?
- No, you answer me. Identify yourself.
Long live the king?
- Barnardo?
- Yes, it's me.
You're right on time.
It's just struck 12.
Go to bed, Francisco.
Thanks for the relief.
It's freezing cold,
and I feel uneasy.
- Has it been quiet on your watch?
- Not even a mouse stirring.
Well, good night.
If you see Horatio and Marcellus,
my fellow guards, tell them to hurry.
FRANCISCO:
I think I hear them. Stop! Who's there?
HORATIO: Friends to this land.
MARCELLUS: And loyal to the Danish king.
Good night to you.
Goodbye, honest soldier.
Who's taking over for you?
Barnardo is taking my place.
Good night to you.
- Hey, Barnardo.
BARNARDO: So, is Horatio there?
Part of him, anyway.
Welcome, Horatio.
Welcome, good Marcellus.
- So, has it shown up again?
- I haven't seen anything.
Horatio says it's just our imagination,
and he won't believe...
...in this terrifying sight
we've seen twice.
So I've asked him to join us
to watch tonight...
...so if it appears again,
he can see it and talk to it.
Nah, it won't show up.
Sit down for a bit,
and let us tell you again...
...the story you're so skeptical about,
what we've seen these past two nights.
Well, let's sit down,
and hear Barnardo tell it.
Last night...
...when that same star
west of the North Star...
...had moved to light up
that part of the sky...
...where it shines now...
...Marcellus and I,
when the bell struck 1 --
Quiet, stop.
Look, it's coming again.
[GASPING]
- Same figure as the dead king.
MARCELLUS: You're a scholar. Talk to it.
BARNARDO:
Doesn't it look like the king?
- Watch it.
- Very much so.
It's terrifying and amazing.
- It wants to be spoken to.
- Talk to it, Horatio.
What are you
that takes over this time of night...
...along with that noble
and warlike appearance...
...that the late king of Denmark
used to have?
By heaven, I command you to speak.
MARCELLUS: It's offended.
BARNARDO: Look, it's walking away.
HORATIO:
Stop, speak, speak, I command you to speak.
MARCELLUS:
It's gone and won't answer.
What's up, Horatio?
You're shaking and look pale.
Isn't this more than just imagination?
What do you think about it?
Honestly, I wouldn't have believed this...
...without seeing it clearly and truly
with my own eyes.
- Doesn't it look like the king?
- Just as much as you look like yourself.
That was exactly the armor he wore
when he fought the ambitious Norway.
He frowned like that once
when during a heated negotiation...
...he struck the sledded Poles
on the ice.
It's strange.
This has happened twice before,
right at this dead hour...
...with a military stride
he's passed by our watch.
What exactly he's planning
I don't know...
...but overall,
in my opinion...
...this signals some strange upheaval
for our state.
Now, please look here,
and tell me, anyone who knows...
...why this strict
and very attentive watch...
...is working the people
of the land so hard every night...
...and why there's such a daily production
of bronze cannons...
...and foreign trade
for weapons...
...why there's such a pressing need for shipbuilders,
whose hard work...
...doesn't even distinguish Sunday
from the rest of the week:
What's going on
that this urgent rush...
...makes the night work alongside
the day...
...who can tell me?
HORATIO:
I can.
At least that's the rumor:
Our last king...
...whose ghost
just appeared to us...
...was, as you know,
challenged by Fortinbras of Norway...
...driven by a strong sense of rivalry...
...to a duel.
In which our brave Hamlet—
For that's how
the world knew him.
—killed this Fortinbras...
...who, by a sealed agreement,
legally confirmed...
...lost all his lands
with his life...
...which he had owned
to the conqueror.
In exchange for which a fair portion...
...was pledged by our king, which would have returned
to Fortinbras' inheritance...
...had he won,
as, by the same agreement...
...and terms outlined,
his lands went to Hamlet.
HORATIO: Now, young Fortinbras,
full of untested spirit and energy...
...has gathered in the outskirts of Norway
here and there...
...a group of landless adventurers
for food and supplies for some venture...
...that has a purpose,
which is none other—
And it's clear to our state.
—but to reclaim from us by force...
...and under compulsion
those lands mentioned before...
...which his father lost.
And this, I believe,
is the main reason for our preparations...
...the cause of this watch,
and the main reason...
...for this urgent activity
and commotion in the land.
I think it really is just like that.
Well, let's hope it works out
that this ominous figure...
...comes armed through our watch
looking so much like the king...
...that was and is the question
of these wars.
It's like a speck that troubles the mind.
In the great and prosperous state of Rome,
a little before the mighty Julius fell...
...the graves were empty
and the shrouded dead...
...squeaked and gibbered
in the Roman streets.
And just like the signs of feared events,
as messengers always preceding fate...
...and a prelude to the coming omen...
...heaven and earth
have shown together...
...to our climate and countrymen.
Like stars with fiery tails
and bloody dew...
...disasters in the sun.
And the wet star...
...on whose influence
Neptune's empire depends...
...was almost sick to doomsday
with an eclipse.
But wait, look.
Look, here it comes again.
I'll confront it even if it harms me.
Stay, illusion.
If you have any sound or voice,
speak to me.
If there's anything good to be done
that might help you and benefit me...
...speak to me.
If you know your country's fate...
...which knowing might help avoid it,
Oh, speak.
Or if you have hidden in your life
stolen treasure in the earth...
...for, they say,
spirits often walk in death...
...speak for it, stay and speak.
Stop it, Marcellus.
- Should I strike it with my spear?
- Do it if it won't stay.
MARCELLUS: It's here.
- It's here.
It's gone.
We do wrong, being so majestic,
to show it violence...
...for it's as invulnerable as air...
...and our pointless blows are a mockery.
It was about to speak
when the rooster crowed.
And then it jumped like a guilty thing...
...at a scary call.
I've heard
the rooster, which is the morning's trumpet...
...with its loud
and high-pitched voice...
...wakes up the god of day...
...and at its warning,
whether in sea or fire, on earth or in air...
...the wandering spirit hurries
back to its limit.
And of the truth in this,
this current sight proved it.
BARNARDO:
It disappeared at the rooster's crow.
Some say that always before
the season comes...
...when our savior's birth
is celebrated...
...the rooster
sings all night long.
And then, they say,
no spirit can walk around...
...the nights are healthy.
Then no planets strike...
...no fairy can take,
nor witch has the power to charm...
...so sacred and so gracious
is this time.
I've heard and partly believe it.
But look, the morning
dressed in reddish-brown...
...walks over the dew
of that high hill to the east.
Let's end our watch,
and if you agree...
...let's tell
what we've seen tonight...
...to young Hamlet.
I bet my life,
this ghost, silent to us, will speak to him.
Do you agree we should tell him,
as it's important for our friendship and duty?
Let's do it, please.
And I know this morning
where we can find him easily.
Even though Hamlet,
our dear brother's death...
...is still fresh in our minds,
and it was right for us...
...to mourn deeply,
and for our whole kingdom...
...to be united in sorrow...
...yet wisdom has
fought with nature...
...so that with the wisest sorrow
we remember him...
...along with thinking
of ourselves.
Therefore, our former sister...
...now our queen...
...the imperial partner
of this warlike state...
...we have
as if with a bittersweet joy...
...with one happy
and one tearful eye...
...with joy at a funeral
and sadness at a wedding...
...balancing delight and grief...
...taken as our wife.
Nor have we ignored
your better judgment...
...which has freely supported
this matter. For all of this, we thank you.
[APPLAUDING]
Now moving on,
you know young Fortinbras...
...underestimating
our strength...
...or thinking
because of our late dear brother's death...
...our state is unstable
and out of order...
...taking advantage of this...
...he hasn't stopped
bothering us with messages...
...demanding the return of lands
lost by his father, with all legal rights...
...to our most valiant brother.
That's enough about him.
[APPLAUDING]
Now for us,
and for this meeting...
...here's the business:
We've written
to Norway, young Fortinbras' uncle...
...who's old and bedridden, barely aware
of his nephew's plans...
...to stop his further actions,
since the troops...
...the lists, and full preparations are all made
from his subjects.
And we now send
you, good Cornelius, and you, Voltemand...
...as messengers
to Old Norway...
...giving you no further authority
to deal with the king...
...beyond what's detailed
in these extended articles.
Farewell, and let your speed
show your commitment.
In that, and in everything else,
we'll show our loyalty.
We have no doubt, goodbye sincerely.
[APPLAUDING]
And now, Laertes,
what's going on with you?
You mentioned some request.
What is it, Laertes?
You can speak to the king
without losing your voice.
What would you ask for, Laertes,
that I wouldn't offer before you even ask?
The head is as close to the heart,
the hand as useful to the mouth...
...as the throne of Denmark is
to your father.
What do you want, Laertes?
My respected Lord,
your permission to return to France...
...from where I willingly came to Denmark
to show my respect at your coronation...
...but now I must admit,
that duty is done...
...my thoughts and desires
turn back to France...
...and I humbly ask
for your permission and forgiveness.
Do you have your father's permission?
What does Polonius say?
He has, my lord,
reluctantly given me his permission...
...after much persuasion, and finally
I gave my difficult consent to his wishes.
I beg you to let him go.
Take your time, Laertes. Use it well,
and make the most of it as you wish.
[APPLAUDING]
But now, my nephew Hamlet...
...and my son.
HAMLET [WHISPERS]:
A little more than family, and less than friendly.
Why do you still seem so gloomy?
HAMLET:
Not at all, my lord...
...I'm just too much in the spotlight.
Good Hamlet...
...take off your dark clothes...
...and look kindly
upon Denmark.
Don't keep your eyes closed
searching for your noble father in the ground.
You know it's common.
Everyone who lives must die,
moving from this world to the next.
Yes, madam, it is common.
If it is,
why does it seem so personal to you?
Seems, madam?
No, it is.
I don't know "seems."
It's not just my dark cloak,
dear mother...
...nor my usual mourning clothes,
nor deep sighs...
...no, nor the tears in my eyes,
nor the sad expression on my face...
...along with all the forms,
moods, and signs of grief...
...that truly show who I am.
These indeed "seem"...
...because they are actions
that anyone could fake.
But I have something inside
that goes beyond appearances.
These are just the outward signs
and the clothes of mourning.
It's admirable
in your nature, Hamlet...
...to pay these respects
to your father.
But you must understand
your father also lost a father.
That father is gone, he's lost.
And the one left behind is bound
by family duty for a time...
...to show proper mourning.
But to keep
stubbornly grieving is a path...
...of disrespectful stubbornness,
it's unmanly grief...
...it shows a will that doesn't align with heaven,
a weak heart, an impatient mind...
...a simple
and uneducated understanding.
For what we know must happen,
and is as common...
...as anything obvious to the senses.
Why should we
in our stubborn resistance...
...take it so hard?
It's a mistake against heaven...
...a mistake against the dead,
a mistake against nature...
...and most unreasonable,
whose common theme...
...is the death of fathers,
and who has always said...
...from the first death
to the one who died today:
"This is how it must be."
We ask you to let go of
this useless grief...
...and think of us as a father.
Let the world know...
...you are the closest
to our throne.
[CHEERING]
And with no less noble love...
...than that which a dear father
has for his son...
...do I feel towards you.
As for your plan
to go back to school in Wittenberg...
...it goes against our wishes...
...and we ask you
to stay...
...here in the joy
and comfort of our presence...
...our top courtier, cousin,
and our son.
Don't let your mother
lose her prayers, Hamlet.
Please stay with us,
don't go to Wittenberg.
I will do my best to obey you, madam.
Why, that's a loving and fair answer.
Be like us in Denmark.
Madam, come.
This gentle and willing agreement from Hamlet
makes me happy.
In honor of this, no joyful toast
that Denmark drinks today...
...but the great cannon
will tell the clouds...
...and the king's toast will echo
through the heavens...
...like earthly thunder.
Come, let's go.
[CHEERING]
Oh, if only this solid flesh
would melt...
...thaw and turn into dew...
...or that God hadn't made a rule
against suicide.
Oh God, God...
...how tired, stale, flat,
and pointless...
...everything in this world seems to me.
Ugh, oh ugh.
It's like a neglected garden
that's overgrown with weeds.
Things wild and unpleasant
completely take over.
I can't believe it's come to this.
It's only been two months since he died.
No, not even two months.
Such a wonderful king he was, compared to this one...
...like a god compared to a beast...
...so loving to my mother...
...that he wouldn't even let
the gentle winds of heaven...
...touch her face too harshly.
Oh, must I remember all this?
She used to cling to him
as if her desire grew...
...the more she had of him,
and yet within a month—
I can't bear to think about it.
Weakness, thy name is woman.
Just a little month,
before those shoes were even old...
...the ones she wore to follow
my poor father's body...
...like Niobe, full of tears,
she, even she—
Oh God, even an animal
that lacks the ability to reason...
...would have mourned longer.
—married my uncle...
...my father's brother...
...but as different from my father
as I am from Hercules...
...within a month...
...before the salt of her fake tears
had dried in her red eyes...
...she got married.
Oh, what wicked speed...
...to rush so quickly
into an incestuous bed.
It won't...
...and it can't turn out well.
But break, my heart...
...because I must stay silent.
Hello to you, sir.
I'm happy to see you doing well.
Horatio.
Or maybe I've forgotten myself.
Yes, it's me, my lord,
and always your humble servant.
Sir, my good friend,
I'll swap that title with you.
So what brings you from Wittenberg,
Horatio? Marcellus.
- My good lord.
- I'm very glad to see you.
Good evening, sir.
But honestly,
what brings you from Wittenberg?
Just a wandering spirit, my good lord.
I wouldn't let your enemy say that,
and you shouldn't make me believe it...
...by saying it yourself. I know you're not a slacker.
So what's your business in Elsinore?
We'll teach you to drink deeply
before you leave.
My lord, I came to see
your father's funeral.
Please don't make fun of me, fellow student.
I think it was to see my mother's wedding.
- Indeed, my lord, it came right after.
- Saving money, saving money, Horatio.
The food from the funeral
was used coldly for the wedding feast.
I wish I had met my worst enemy in heaven
before I ever saw that day, Horatio.
My father.
I think I see my father.
Where, my lord?
In my mind's eye, Horatio.
I saw him once.
He was a great king.
He was a man.
Consider him in every way...
...I will never see someone like him again.
My lord...
...I think...
...I saw him last night.
Saw?
Who?
My lord, the king...
...your father.
The king, my father?
Hold your amazement for a moment
and listen carefully while I tell...
...with the testimony of these gentlemen,
this wonder to you.
For God's sake, let me hear it.
For two nights in a row, these gentlemen,
Marcellus and Barnardo, on their watch...
...in the dead of night,
encountered this.
A figure like your father,
fully armed from head to toe...
...appears before them,
and with a solemn march...
...walks slowly and with dignity past them.
Three times he passed by their overwhelmed
and frightened eyes...
...within arm's reach,
while they were almost...
...frozen with fear,
stood silent and didn't speak to him.
They told me this in strict confidence...
...and I joined them on the third night
to keep watch...
...where, as they described,
both in time...
...and form of the figure,
every word was true...
...the ghost appeared.
I knew your father.
- These hands are not more similar.
- But where was this?
On the platform where we kept watch.
- Did you speak to it?
- My lord, I did.
But it didn't answer.
Yet once I thought...
...it lifted its head and seemed
like it was going to speak...
...but just then the morning rooster
crowed loudly...
...and at the sound, it quickly shrank away
and disappeared from our sight.
That's very strange.
As I live, my honored lord, it's true.
We thought it was our duty
to let you know about it.
Indeed, indeed, gentlemen.
But this worries me.
Are you on watch tonight?
- We are.
- Armed, you say?
BOTH: Yes, my lord, he was armed.
- From head to toe?
- From head to foot.
- Then you didn't see his face.
Oh yes, my lord, his visor was up.
How did he look? Was he frowning?
- He looked more sad than angry.
- Was he pale or flushed?
- Very pale.
- Did he keep his eyes on you?
Yes, he did.
I wish I had been there.
- It would have really surprised you.
- Very likely...
...very likely.
- Did he stay long?
- Long enough to count to a hundred.
- Longer, longer.
- Not when I saw it.
His beard was gray, right?
It was like I remember it in life,
a dark gray with silver.
I'll watch tonight.
Maybe it'll appear again.
I'm sure it will.
If it looks like my noble father...
...I'll speak to it even if hell itself
opens up...
...and tells me to stay silent.
I ask you all,
if you've kept this sight a secret so far...
...keep it that way...
...and whatever else
happens tonight...
...understand it but don't speak of it.
I'll repay your kindness.
So goodbye for now.
I'll meet you on the platform between 11 and 12.
I'll see you then.
- Our duty to you, sir.
- Your loyalty, as mine is to you.
Goodbye.
HAMLET:
My father's ghost in armor.
Something's wrong.
I suspect foul play.
I wish it were night already.
Until then, stay calm, my soul.
Bad deeds will come to light...
...even if they're buried deep,
for all to see.
My things are packed. Goodbye.
And sister, as the winds are favorable
and the ship is ready, don't delay...
...but write to me.
Do you doubt that?
As for Hamlet and his affection,
consider it a youthful whim...
...a fleeting passion,
exciting but not lasting...
...like a flower that blooms briefly,
nothing more.
- Nothing more than that?
- Think of it as nothing more.
For as we grow, we don't just grow
in size and strength...
...but as his body matures,
the mind and soul...
...grow as well.
Maybe he loves you now...
...and right now nothing tarnishes
his intentions. But you should worry...
...considering his status,
his choices aren't his alone...
...because he's bound by his birth.
He can't, like people who aren't valued...
...make decisions for himself,
because his choice affects...
...the well-being and stability
of the entire state.
So his decision must be
limited...
...to the opinions and consent of the group
that he leads.
So if he says he loves you,
you should only believe it...
...as much as his actions and position
support his words...
...which is only as far
as the main opinion in Denmark allows.
Consider what damage
your reputation might suffer...
...if you listen too easily
to his sweet talk...
...or fall for him...
...or give up your purity
to his uncontrolled persistence.
Be careful, Ophelia, be careful, my dear sister...
...and keep your feelings in check,
away from the risks of desire.
Even the most cautious girl is too reckless
if she reveals her beauty to the night.
Even virtue itself doesn't escape
slanderous attacks.
The worm harms the early buds of spring
too often before they even bloom...
...and in the morning
and fresh dew of youth...
...harmful influences
are most likely.
Be cautious then. The safest path is to be wary.
Youth rebels against itself,
even if no one else is around.
I'll keep this good advice
as a guard to my heart.
But, dear brother,
don't be like some hypocritical preachers...
...who show me the difficult
and thorny path to heaven...
...while like a puffed-up
and careless playboy...
...they walk the easy path
of pleasure...
...and ignore their own advice.
Oh, don't worry about me.
- I've stayed too long.
POLONIUS: Still here, Laertes?
But here comes my father.
A double blessing is a double gift.
It's a good time for a second farewell.
Get on board, get on board, for shame.
The wind is in your favor,
and they're waiting for you.
Here's my blessing for you.
And remember these few rules,
make sure you remember them.
Don't speak every thought you have...
...or act on every impulse.
Be friendly but not overly familiar.
The friends you have,
and have proven themselves...
...hold them close to your heart
like "hoops of steel"...
...but don't wear yourself out
by entertaining...
...every new,
untested friend.
Avoid getting into fights,
but if you do...
...handle it so that your opponent
will think twice about challenging you.
Listen to everyone,
but speak to few.
Take everyone's opinion,
but keep your own judgment.
Dress as well as you can afford,
but not too flashy.
Rich but not showy.
Because clothes often make the man...
...and they are in France
of the highest rank and status...
...are the most distinguished
and generous leaders in that regard.
Don't be a borrower or a lender...
...because loans often result in losing
both the money and the friend...
...and borrowing weakens
financial responsibility.
Above all else:
Be true to yourself...
...and just like night follows day,
you won't be false to anyone.
Goodbye.
May my blessing guide you in this.
I humbly take my leave, my lord.
It's time for you to go.
Go. Your servants are waiting.
Goodbye, Ophelia...
...and remember well
what I've told you.
It's locked in my memory...
...and you will keep
the key to it.
Goodbye.
POLONIUS:
What did he say to you, Ophelia?
[BELL CHIMING]
OPHELIA:
If it pleases you...
...something about Lord Hamlet.
POLONIUS:
Indeed, well considered.
I've been told that he has recently
spent private time with you...
...and you have been
very open and generous with him.
If that's true-- As it's been told to me,
and as a warning.
--I must tell you
you don't understand yourself clearly enough...
...as my daughter should
and for your own honor.
What's going on between you two?
Tell me the truth.
He has, my lord, recently...
...shown many signs
of affection towards me.
POLONIUS:
Affection, nonsense.
You speak like a naive girl
inexperienced in such risky situations.
Do you believe his "affection"
as you call it?
I don't know, my lord,
what to think.
Well, I'll teach you:
think of yourself as a child...
...for believing his affections
are genuine when they're not.
Value yourself highly...
...or, to put it plainly, you'll make me look foolish.
My lord, he has pursued me with love
in an honorable way--
Yes, you could call it "fashion."
Enough, enough.
And he has supported his words
with almost all the sacred vows.
Yes, traps to catch the naive.
I know when passion is strong
how freely the soul...
...makes promises.
These flames, daughter,
give more light than heat, and fade quickly...
...even as they promise, while being made,
you must not mistake them for true fire.
From now on, be less available
with your presence.
Value your time more
than just a simple conversation.
As for Lord Hamlet,
remember that he is young...
...and he can roam more freely
than you are allowed.
In short, Ophelia...
...don't trust his promises,
because they are like agents...
...not true to the appearance
they present...
...but just asking for improper favors...
...pretending to be holy and sincere
to deceive you better.
That's all. I don't want you,
to put it simply, from now on...
...to waste any free time...
...by speaking or chatting
with Lord Hamlet.
Pay attention, I'm warning you.
Let's go.
OPHELIA:
I will obey...
...my lord.
HAMLET:
The air is biting, it's really cold.
It's sharp and biting.
- What time is it now?
- I think it's almost midnight.
No, it's already struck.
Really? I didn't hear it.
Then it's almost the time
when the ghost usually appears.
[RUMBLING ABOVE]
[WHISPERS]
What does this mean, my lord?
HAMLET: The king is awake tonight
and is partying...
...having a feast,
and the rowdy dance begins.
And as he drinks his wine...
...the drums and trumpets loudly announce
the success of his toast.
- Is it a tradition?
- Yes, indeed it is.
But in my opinion, even though I'm from here
and grew up with it...
...it's a tradition better broken
than followed.
This heavy partying, east and west...
...makes us criticized
and judged by other countries...
...they call us drunkards,
and with insulting words...
...tarnish our reputation.
And it actually diminishes
our accomplishments...
...even when they're great,
the essence and value of our character.
It often happens in individuals...
...that due to some flaw
in their nature...
...from birth, which isn't their fault
since nature decides their origin...
...by the excess
of some trait...
...often breaking down the barriers
and defenses of reason...
...or by some habit,
that overly influences...
...their usual behavior,
that these people...
...having, I say, the mark of one flaw,
whether it's nature's doing or fate's...
...their other virtues, even if as pure as grace,
as numerous as one can have...
...will in general judgment
be tainted...
...by that specific fault.
A small amount of evil
can overshadow all the good...
...to its own disgrace.
HORATIO:
Look, my lord, it's coming.
It's signaling you to go with it...
...as if it wants to share something
with you alone.
Look how politely it gestures for you to move to a more distant spot.
- But don't go with it.
- No, definitely not.
- It won't speak. Then I'll follow it.
- Don't, my lord.
Why should I be afraid?
I don't value my life much at all...
...and as for my soul, what can it do to that,
since it's as immortal as the ghost itself?
It's beckoning me again.
I'll follow it.
What if it lures you to the water?
Or to the top of the cliff
that hangs over the sea?
And there it might take on
some other terrifying form...
...that could rob you
of your sanity...
...and drive you mad?
Think about it.
This very place puts desperate thoughts...
...into everyone's mind
who looks down at the sea...
...and hears it roar below.
- It's still calling me. Go on, I'll follow you.
- You can't go.
- Let go of me.
- Listen to reason. You can't go.
My destiny calls out to me.
And makes every tiny artery in my body
as strong as the Nemean lion's sinew.
I'm still being called. Let go of me, gentlemen.
By heaven,
I'll make a ghost of anyone who stops me.
I said, let go!
Go on, I'll follow you.
- He's getting reckless with his imagination.
- Let's follow him. It's not right to just let him go.
Let's go after him. What will come of this?
Something is wrong
in the state of Denmark.
Heaven will guide it.
No, let's follow him.
HAMLET:
Angels and protectors, defend us.
Whether you're a good spirit
or a damned ghost...
...bringing breezes from heaven
or blasts from hell...
...whether your intentions are evil or kind,
you come in such a form...
...that I will speak to you.
I'll call you Hamlet,
king, father, royal Dane.
Oh, answer me!
Don't let me die in ignorance...
...but tell me why your sacred bones,
buried in death...
...have broken through their shroud...
...why the tomb
where we saw you peacefully buried...
...has opened its heavy marble jaws
to spit you out again.
What does this mean...
...that you, a dead body,
fully armored...
...are revisiting the moonlit night,
making it terrifying...
...and causing us, mere humans,
to tremble so horribly...
...with thoughts beyond
our understanding?
Tell me, why is this? Why?
What should we do?
Where are you leading me?
Speak.
I'll go no further.
GHOST: Listen to me.
HAMLET: I will.
GHOST:
My time is almost here...
...when I must give myself up...
...to sulfurous and tormenting flames.
HAMLET:
Oh, poor ghost.
GHOST: Don't pity me, but listen closely
to what I'm about to tell you.
HAMLET:
Speak, I'm ready to listen.
GHOST: You must also be ready for revenge
when you hear what I have to say.
HAMLET:
What?
I am your father's spirit...
...doomed for a certain time
to wander at night...
...and during the day
trapped in fires...
...until the terrible deeds
I did in my lifetime...
...are burned and purified away.
But I'm not allowed
to reveal the secrets of my prison...
...or I could tell a story
whose simplest word...
...would tear at your soul,
freeze your young blood...
...make your eyes pop out
like stars from their sockets...
...make your hair stand up...
...and each individual hair
stand on end...
...like quills on an angry porcupine.
But this eternal revelation can't be
shared with living ears.
Listen, Hamlet, listen, oh listen.
- If you ever loved your dear father--
- Oh, God!
Avenge his horrible
and unnatural murder.
- Murder?
- Murder most foul, as it always is...
...but this one is especially foul, strange,
and unnatural.
Hurry to find out...
...so that with wings as swift
as thought or love...
...I can rush to my revenge.
I find you ready...
...and you'd be slower than the lazy weed...
...that grows comfortably on the banks of Lethe,
if you didn't act on this.
Now, Hamlet, listen.
It's been said that,
while sleeping in my orchard...
...a snake bit me.
So the whole of Denmark...
...is misled by a false account of my death.
But know this, noble young man,
the snake that took your father's life...
...now wears his crown.
Oh, my prophetic soul. My uncle?
GHOST: Yes, that incestuous,
adulterous beast...
...with his cunning words,
and treacherous gifts--
Oh, wicked wit and gifts,
that have the power to seduce.
--won over to his shameful desires...
...the will of my seemingly
virtuous queen.
Oh, Hamlet...
...what a downfall that was.
From me, whose love was so noble
that it matched...
...the vow
I made to her in marriage...
...to fall for a wretch...
...whose natural talents were lacking
compared to mine.
But virtue will never be swayed...
...even if immorality tries to seduce it
in a heavenly form...
...just as lust,
even when connected to a radiant angel...
...will satisfy itself in a heavenly bed...
...and then feed on trash.
But wait, I think I smell
the morning air.
Let me be brief.
While I was sleeping in my orchard,
as I usually did in the afternoon...
...during my peaceful time, your uncle snuck in...
...with a vial of cursed poison...
...and poured it into my ears...
...the deadly liquid...
...which has such a hostile effect on human blood...
...that as quickly as mercury...
...it flows through
the body's natural pathways...
...and with sudden force
it thickens...
...and curdles, like sour drops in milk,
the thin and healthy blood.
That's what it did to mine.
And a horrible rash covered me...
...like a leper,
with a disgusting and loathsome crust...
...all over my smooth body.
So I was, while sleeping...
...by my brother's hand...
...robbed of life, crown, and queen...
...all at once...
...cut off
even in the middle of my sins...
...without last rites, unprepared, unanointed...
...no chance to make amends,
but sent to my fate...
...with all my flaws still on me.
Oh, horrible...
...oh, horrible...
...most horrible.
If you have any natural feelings, don't let it happen.
Don't let the royal bed of Denmark become
a place for lust and cursed incest.
But however you pursue this task...
...don't corrupt your mind...
...or let your soul plot
against your mother.
Leave her to heaven...
...and to the guilt
that will torment her...
...to prick and sting her.
Farewell for now.
The glow-worm shows that morning is near,
and its weak light begins to fade.
Goodbye, goodbye, Hamlet.
Remember me.
Oh, all you hosts of heaven.
Oh earth. What else?
And should I include hell?
Oh no.
Hold on, hold on, my heart...
...and you, my muscles, don't grow old suddenly,
but keep me strong.
Remember me?
Yes, you poor ghost...
...as long as I have a memory
in this troubled mind.
Remember you? Yes...
...I'll erase all unimportant memories
from my mind...
...all sayings from books, all forms,
all past impressions...
...that youth and experience
have recorded there...
...and your command will be the only thing
in the book of my mind...
...unmixed with lesser things.
Yes, by heaven.
Oh, most wicked woman!
Oh villain, villain, smiling, damned villain.
My notes...
...it's fitting I write it down
that someone can smile and smile and still be a villain.
At least I'm sure
it can happen in Denmark.
So uncle, there you are.
Now to my promise:
It is, "Goodbye, goodbye...
...remember me."
I've sworn it.
- My lord!
- Lord Hamlet!
- May heaven protect him.
- So be it.
Hey, hey, my lord!
Hey, hey, boy.
- Come on, bird, come!
- How are you, my lord?
- What's the news?
- Oh, it's amazing.
- My lord, tell us.
- You'll reveal it.
- Not me, my lord, by heaven.
- Nor me, my lord.
What do you say then,
would anyone have ever thought it?
- But you'll keep it secret?
- Yes, by heaven, my lord.
There's not a single villain in all of Denmark
who isn't a complete scoundrel.
We don't need a ghost to come from the grave
to tell us that.
You're absolutely right.
Without any more fuss
I think it's best we shake hands and part ways...
...you go where your work
and desires lead you--
For everyone has work and desires,
whatever they may be.
--and as for me,
I'll go pray.
These are just wild and crazy words.
I'm sorry if they offend you deeply,
yes, truly, deeply.
- There's no offense.
- Yes, by Saint Patrick, there is, Horatio...
...and a lot of offense too.
Regarding this vision here,
it's an honest ghost, let me tell you that.
As for your desire
to know what's between us...
...control it as best you can.
And now, good friends,
since you're friends, scholars, and soldiers...
...grant me one small request.
What is it, my lord? We will.
Never reveal
what you've seen tonight.
- My lord, we won't.
- No, but swear it.
Honestly, my lord, not me.
Nor me, my lord, not me.
On my sword.
But we've already sworn, my lord.
Yes, on my sword, indeed.
GHOST:
Swear!
Oh, hey, do you hear that, boy? Are you saying that?
Are you there, old friend?
You hear this guy in the basement.
Agree to swear.
Suggest the oath, my lord.
Never speak of what you've seen.
Swear on my sword.
GHOST:
Swear.
[SPEAKS IN LATIN]
Then let's move to another spot.
Come here, gentlemen,
and put your hands on my sword again.
Never speak of what you've heard,
swear on my sword.
GHOST: Swear.
- Well said, old mole.
Can you dig so fast?
A good digger.
Let's move again, good friends.
Oh, day and night,
this is really strange.
And so, as a stranger,
welcome it.
There are more things
in heaven and earth, Horatio...
...than we can imagine in our philosophy.
But come on.
Here as before,
never, so help you mercy...
...no matter how strange or odd
I might act--
As I might later decide
to act crazy.
--that when you see me, you never shall
with crossed arms...
...or by shaking your head,
or by saying something vague like...
..."We know,"
or "We could if we wanted to"...
...or "If we choose to speak,"
or "There are, if they might"...
...or such unclear hints, to show
that you know anything about me.
Don't do this...
...so grace and mercy...
...help you when you need it most...
...swear.
GHOST:
Swear.
[RUMBLING]
[PANTING]
Rest...
...rest...
...troubled spirit.
So gentlemen,
with all my love, I commend myself to you...
...and whatever a poor man like Hamlet can do...
...to show
his love and friendship to you...
...God willing, won't be lacking.
Let's go in together...
...and keep your fingers on your lips,
please.
The times are messed up.
Oh, cursed fate...
...that I was ever born to fix it.
Come on.
Let's go together.
Give him this money
and these notes, Reynaldo.
I will, my lord.
You'll do very well,
good Reynaldo...
...before you visit him, to ask around
about his behavior.
My lord, I planned to do that.
Good, well said, very well said.
Listen, sir,
first find out which Danes are in Paris...
...and how, and who, what they're doing,
and where they hang out...
...who they spend time with, and how much they spend.
And by asking these questions
and gathering information...
...if they know my son...
...get closer to the truth
than direct questions would.
Pretend you know him
just a little bit...
...like this: "I know his father and his friends,
and sort of know him."
- Are you following this, Reynaldo?
- Yes, very well, my lord.
"And sort of know him, but,"
you might say, "not very well...
...but if it's who I think, he's quite wild,
into this and that."
And then make up
whatever stories you like--
But none so bad
that they ruin his reputation. Be careful about that.
--but, sir, such harmless,
wild, and common mistakes...
...that are typical and well-known
among young people.
- Like gambling, my lord?
- Yes, or drinking, fencing, swearing...
...fighting, womanizing.
You can go that far.
My lord, that would ruin his reputation.
No, not if you present it
in the right way.
Don't accuse him of something serious,
like being unfaithful--
That's not what I mean.
--but mention his faults so cleverly
that they seem like the flaws of freedom...
...the excitement and outburst
of a passionate mind...
...a wildness in untamed youth,
common to everyone.
- But, my good lord--
- Why should you do this?
Yes, my lord.
I want to know that.
Well, sir, here's my plan,
and I think it's a clever one.
By mentioning these minor faults
about my son...
...as if it's something
slightly tarnished...
...notice, the person you're talking to,
the one you're trying to get information from...
...having seen these mentioned behaviors
in the young man you're describing...
...will surely
agree with you by saying:
"Good sir," or something like that, or "friend,"
or "gentleman"...
...depending on the way people speak
in that place.
Very good, my lord.
And then, sir, he does this. He does--
What was I about to say?
Oh, I was about to say something.
Where did I stop?
At "agrees with you"...
...at "friend," or something like that, and "gentleman."
At "agrees with you."
Yes, indeed,
he agrees with me like this:
"I know the guy,
I saw him yesterday"—
Or the day before,
Or whenever.
—"with so-and-so, and like you said...
...there was some gambling,
he got caught up in drinking...
...or had a fight at tennis," or maybe,
"I saw him go into a certain place"...
...like, a brothel, or something like that.
See, your little lie
catches the truth.
And that's how we smart people
and those who are clever...
...with tricks
and indirect methods...
...find out the truth.
So with my previous advice,
you'll guide my son.
- You understand, right?
- Yes, my lord, I do.
God be with you. Take care.
Thank you, my lord.
Watch his behavior yourself.
I will, my lord.
And let him focus on his music.
Alright, my lord.
Goodbye.
OPHELIA:
My lord!
POLONIUS:
What's going on, Ophelia?
Oh my lord, I was so scared.
Scared of what, for God's sake?
My lord, as I was sewing
in my room...
...Lord Hamlet,
with his jacket all undone...
...no hat on his head,
his stockings dirty...
...not fastened, and hanging
down to his ankle...
...pale as his shirt,
his knees knocking together...
...and with such a pitiful look...
...as if he had come from hell
to talk about horrors...
...he came to me.
- Crazy because of your love?
- My lord, I don't know.
- But I really do fear it.
- What did he say?
He grabbed me by the wrist
and held me tight...
...then stretched out
his arm...
...and with his other hand
over his forehead...
...he stared at my face
like he was trying to memorize it.
He stayed like that for a long time.
Finally, he gave my arm a little shake...
...and nodded his head
up and down three times...
...he let out a sigh
so deep and sad...
...it seemed to shake his whole body
and end his life.
After that, he let me go...
...and, with his head
turned over his shoulder...
...he seemed to find his way
without looking...
...because he went outside
without using his eyes...
...and until the end
kept his gaze on me.
POLONIUS:
Come on.
Come with me.
I'm going to find the king.
This is the intense madness of love,
which is so intense it destroys itself...
...and drives people
to desperate actions...
...as often as any emotion on earth
that troubles us.
I'm sorry.
[OPHELIA CRYING]
Have you said anything harsh to him recently?
No, my lord,
but as you instructed...
...I rejected his letters and refused
to see him.
That's what made him crazy.
I'm sorry I didn't pay more attention
and use better judgment...
...to understand him.
I was afraid he was just playing around
and meant to hurt you.
But curse my jealousy.
Honestly, it's typical for people our age
to overthink things...
...just like it's common for younger people
to lack wisdom.
[OPHELIA SOBBING]
Let's go to the king.
This needs to be known,
because keeping it secret might cause...
...more pain to hide
than trouble to reveal.
Let's go.
Welcome, dear Rosencrantz
and Guildenstern.
Besides the fact that we really wanted
to see you...
...we urgently needed your help,
so we sent for you quickly.
You've heard something
about Hamlet's change.
That's what I'll call it...
...since neither his appearance nor his mind
is the same as it was.
What could be causing it...
...besides his father's death,
that has made him...
...so confused about himself,
I can't imagine.
I ask you both...
...since you grew up with him...
...and have been close
to him and his personality...
...to stay here at our court...
...for a little while, so with your company
you can cheer him up and find out...
...if there's anything unknown to us
that's bothering him...
...that, once revealed, we can help with.
Good gentlemen,
he has talked a lot about you...
...and I'm sure there are no two people
he cares about more.
If you would be so kind
to spend some time with us...
...for the benefit of our hopes...
...your visit will be rewarded
as a king should.
Both of you could,
by the power you have over us...
...demand rather than ask.
But we both agree,
and we offer ourselves completely...
...to serve you freely
at your command.
Thank you, Rosencrantz
and kind Guildenstern.
Thank you, Guildenstern
and kind Rosencrantz.
And I ask you to immediately visit
my greatly changed son.
Go, take these gentlemen
to where Hamlet is.
May the heavens make our presence and actions
pleasant and helpful to him.
GERTRUDE:
Yes, amen.
POLONIUS: The ambassadors from
Norway, my lord, have returned happily.
- You've always brought good news.
POLONIUS: Have I, my lord?
Rest assured, my good king,
I hold my duty as dear as my soul...
...both to my God
and to my gracious king.
And I believe—
Unless my mind
no longer follows political matters as well...
...as it used to.
—that I have discovered
the real reason for Hamlet's madness.
Oh, tell me that, I really want to hear it.
Let the ambassadors in first.
My news will be the highlight
of this great occasion.
Well, go greet them,
and bring them in.
He tells me, my dear Gertrude,
that he has found...
...the root cause
of your son's troubles.
I suspect it's nothing but the obvious...
...his father's death
and our rushed marriage.
Well, we'll get to the bottom of it.
CLAUDIUS:
Welcome, my good friends.
Tell me, Voltemand,
what's the news from our brother Norway?
A very positive return of greetings and intentions.
At first, he sent orders to stop
his nephew's troops...
...which seemed to him
to be preparing against the Poles.
But upon closer inspection, he realized
it was against Your Highness.
Upset by this,
that his illness, age, and weakness...
...were being used as an excuse,
he sent out orders...
...to arrest Fortinbras, which he quickly obeyed,
received a reprimand from Norway...
...and, in the end,
promised his uncle never again...
...to raise arms
against Your Majesty.
As a result, Old Norway,
overjoyed...
...gave him 3000 crowns annually...
...and the authority
to use those soldiers...
...as previously gathered,
against the Poles...
...with a request further detailed here...
...that you allow safe passage
through your lands for this mission...
...with the conditions of safety and approval
as outlined.
We are pleased with this.
And at a more convenient time, we'll read,
respond, and consider this matter.
Meanwhile, we thank you
for your efforts.
Go rest.
Tonight we'll celebrate together.
Welcome back home.
This matter is well resolved.
My lord and madam, to discuss
what majesty should be, what duty is...
...why day is day, night is night,
and time is time...
...would be nothing but wasting
night, day, and time.
Therefore, since being brief
is the essence of intelligence...
...and long-windedness the unnecessary details...
...I will be brief.
Your noble son is insane.
"Madness" is what I call it, because what else is madness but being mad?
But let's move on.
- Get to the point with less embellishment.
Madam, I promise I'm not using any embellishment.
It's true that he's mad.
It's a shame, and a shame it's true.
A silly expression,
but let's leave it, as I won't use embellishment.
Let's agree he's mad, then.
And now we need to
find out what's causing this.
Or better yet, "what's causing this flaw,"
because this flawed effect has a cause.
So that's where we are, and here's what's left.
Consider this.
Ophelia.
I have a daughter—
I have her while she's mine.
—who, in her duty and obedience, listen,
has given me this.
Now think about it and guess.
"To...
...the...
...heavenly and my soul's idol...
...the most beautiful Ophelia."
That's a bad phrase, a terrible phrase...
..."beautiful" is a terrible phrase.
But listen to this.
"These...
...in...
...her excellent...
...white bosom, these."
Did this come from Hamlet to her?
Good madam, hold on a moment.
I'll be honest.
"Doubt the stars are fire,
doubt the sun moves...
...doubt truth is a liar,
but never doubt I love you."
Dear Ophelia, I'm bad with these words.
I don't have the skill to express my feelings.
But that I love you most...
...O most of all, believe it.
Goodbye, goodbye.
Yours forever....
"Most dear lady,
while this body is his, Hamlet."
In obedience,
my daughter has shown me this...
...and more of his advances...
...as they happened over time,
by means, and place...
...all told to me.
How has she received his love?
- What do you think of me?
- As a man who is faithful and honorable.
I want to prove that.
But what would you think,
when I saw this passionate love developing...
...as I noticed it,
before my daughter told me...
...what would you, or your queen, think
if I had acted like a piece of furniture?
Or kept my heart
silent and unresponsive?
Or watched this with idle eyes,
what would you think?
No, I took action,
and I spoke to my young mistress like this:
"Prince Hamlet is way out of your league.
This can't happen."
And then I gave her instructions,
to keep herself away from him...
...not to allow any messengers,
and accept no gifts.
She followed my advice,
and he, rejected—long story short.
—fell into a depression, then stopped eating...
...then stayed up all night,
then grew weak...
...and eventually, by this decline,
into the madness he's now in...
...and we're all upset about.
- Do you think that's the reason?
- It could be. Seems likely.
Has there ever been a time—
I'd really like to know.
—when I said, "That's the case,"
and it turned out to be wrong?
- Not that I know of.
- Take this from me if I'm wrong.
If the situation leads me, I'll discover
where the truth is hidden...
...even if it's buried deep.
How can we investigate further?
You know, sometimes he walks
for four hours straight here in the lobby.
Yes, he does.
At that time,
I'll send my daughter to him.
You and I should hide behind a curtain.
Watch what happens.
If he doesn't love her
and hasn't lost his mind because of it...
...then I shouldn't be an advisor,
but just run a farm.
- Let's test it.
- But look...
...oh, here comes the poor guy
reading sadly.
Please, both of you, go away.
I'll approach him soon.
Give me a moment.
How are you, my good Lord Hamlet?
[GASPS]
Well, thank you.
Do you recognize me, my lord?
Yes, very well. You're a fish seller.
- No, I'm not, my lord.
- Then I wish you were as honest as one.
- Honest, my lord?
- Yes, sir.
Being honest, in this world,
is like being one in 10,000.
That's very true, my lord.
For if the sun breeds maggots
in a dead dog...
...being a god kissing a corpse.
Do you have a daughter?
I do, my lord.
Don't let her walk in the sun.
Conception is a blessing,
but your daughter might conceive...
Friend...
...be careful.
What do you think of that?
Still going on about my daughter.
Yet he didn't recognize me at first.
He said I was a fish seller.
He's really gone, really gone.
And honestly, when I was young,
I went through a lot because of love...
...almost like this.
I'll talk to him again.
- What are you reading, my lord?
- Just words.
Words.
- Words.
- What's the topic, my lord?
- Between whom?
- I mean, what are you reading about?
Insults, sir. This sarcastic writer
says here that old men have gray beards...
...that their faces are wrinkled...
...their eyes leak thick amber
and plum-tree sap...
...and that they lack wisdom,
along with having weak legs.
All of which, sir,
although I strongly believe...
...I don't think it's right to write it
down like this.
Because you, sir,
will grow old like me...
...unless you could walk backward like a crab.
Though this seems crazy,
there's a method to it.
- Would you like to come inside, my lord?
- Into my grave?
Well, that is out of the air.
Sometimes his responses are so clever.
A kind of luck
that madness often hits on...
...which reason and sanity can't
deliver so successfully.
I'll leave him and quickly plan...
...a meeting
between him and my daughter.
My lord?
My lord, I'll be taking my leave now.
You can't take anything from me, sir,
that I'd be happier to part with.
Except my life.
Goodbye, my lord.
These tiresome old fools.
My honored lord!
You're going to find Lord Hamlet.
There he is.
My honored lord!
[CHUCKLING]
My dearest lord.
HAMLET:
My excellent good friends.
How are you, Guildenstern?
Rosencrantz?
Good guys, how are you both?
Like the average people of the world.
Happy that we're not too happy,
we're not at the top of Fortune's hat.
- Nor at the bottom of her shoes?
- Neither, my lord.
You're around her waist,
in the middle of her favors?
Actually, we're in her private parts.
In Fortune's secret parts? Very true,
she's a whore. What's the news?
Nothing, my lord,
except the world has become honest.
Then judgment day is near.
But your news isn't true.
Let me ask specifically.
What have you done to deserve
being sent to prison by Fortune?
- Prison?
- Denmark's a prison.
- Then the world is one.
- A pretty big one.
With many boundaries,
sections, and cells...
- ...Denmark being one of the worst.
- We don't think so, my lord.
Well, then it's not one to you...
...because nothing is good or bad
except how you think about it.
To me, it's like a prison.
Well, your ambition is what makes it feel that way.
It's too small for your mind.
Oh God, I could be confined
in a tiny space...
...and still think of myself
as a king of endless space...
...if it weren't for my bad dreams.
Those dreams are actually ambition.
Because the essence of ambition
is just the shadow of a dream.
A dream itself is only a shadow.
And I think ambition
is so light and airy...
...it's just a shadow's shadow.
Well, then our beggars are the real people...
...and our kings and heroes
are just the beggars' shadows.
Shall we go to the court?
Honestly, I can't figure it out.
- We'll wait for you.
- That's not necessary.
I won't group you with the rest
of my servants...
...because, to be honest,
I'm poorly served.
But as friends,
why are you in Elsinore?
To visit you, my lord. No other reason.
I'm such a beggar,
I'm even poor in thanks...
...but thank you.
And really, dear friends,
my thanks are worth very little.
Were you sent for?
Is it your own decision?
Is this a free visit?
Come on, be honest with me.
Come on, come on. Speak up.
What should we say, my lord?
Anything but the truth!
You were sent for.
I can see it in your faces, and
you're not good at hiding it.
- The king and queen sent for you.
- Why, my lord?
You have to tell me.
Let me ask you,
by our friendship...
...by our shared youth...
...by the bond
of our lasting love...
...and by anything else
that might compel you...
...be honest and direct with me
whether you were sent for or not.
- What do you say?
- Well, then, I've got my eye on you.
If you care about me, don't hold back.
My lord, we were sent for.
HAMLET:
I'll tell you why.
So my guesswork
won't spoil your secret...
...and you won't lose any favor
with the king and queen.
Lately, I've--
But I don't know why.
--lost all my happiness,
stopped all my usual activities.
And honestly, it weighs so heavily
on my mood...
...that this beautiful earth...
...seems like a barren cliff to me.
This amazing sky, the air...
...look at it,
this magnificent overhanging sky...
...this magnificent ceiling...
...decorated with golden light.
Why, it seems to me like nothing more...
...than a disgusting and harmful
collection of vapors.
What an amazing creation is a human.
How noble in reasoning...
...how limitless in abilities...
...in shape and movement
how clear and admirable...
...in action, how like an angel...
...in understanding, how like a god...
...the beauty of the world...
...the best of all animals.
And yet, to me...
...what is this essence...
...of dust?
People don't bring me joy.
No, not women either,
even though your smile suggests otherwise.
My lord, I wasn't thinking about that.
Why did you laugh, then,
when I said, "People don't bring me joy"?
To consider, my lord,
if you don't enjoy people...
...what little entertainment
the actors will get from you.
We met them on the way and now
they are coming to offer their services to you.
The one who plays the king will be welcome.
His Majesty will receive my tribute.
The daring knight
will use his sword and shield...
...the lover won't sigh for free...
...the funny man
will finish his part peacefully...
...the clown will make those laugh
whose lungs are easily amused...
...and the lady will speak her mind freely,
or the poetry will suffer for it.
What actors are they?
ROSENCRANTZ: The same ones you used to
enjoy, the city's tragedians.
How come they're traveling?
Their standing, both in reputation
and profit, was better when they stayed put.
Their restriction comes
because of recent changes.
Do they still have the same reputation
they did when I was in the city?
- Are they still popular?
- They are not.
HAMLET:
Well, how did that happen? Are they getting outdated?
Their efforts
remain the same as before.
But there is, sir, a group of children...
...little performers who shout at the top
of their lungs and get applause for it.
These are now in style...
...and they criticize the usual stages...
...so much that many sword-wearers are scared of
writers and hardly go there.
Are they children? Who supports them?
How are they funded?
Will they continue acting
only as long as they can sing?
Won't they later say, if they
become regular actors—
As is likely,
if their opportunities don't improve.
—that their writers wrong them by making them
speak against their own future?
Honestly, there's been a lot of fuss
on both sides.
The nation doesn't see it as wrong
to provoke them into arguments.
There wasn't any money offered for the argument
unless the poet and actor started fighting.
- Is that possible?
- There's been a lot of brainpower wasted.
And do the boys win in the end?
ROSENCRANTZ: Yes, they do,
my lord, even Hercules and his burden too.
Well, that's not very surprising.
Because my uncle is the king of Denmark...
...and those who would mock him
when my father was alive...
...now pay 20, 40, 50, a hundred ducats
each for a small picture of him.
[LAUGHING]
'Sblood, there's something more
than natural about this, if philosophy could figure it out.
[PEOPLE CHUCKLING]
Here come the actors.
Welcome to Elsinore.
Shake hands. The custom of welcome
is all about fashion and ceremony.
Let me greet you in this manner,
so my welcome to the actors—
Which must be shown outwardly.
—doesn't seem more like entertainment
than yours.
But my uncle-father and aunt-mother
are mistaken.
In what way, my dear lord?
I'm only crazy when the wind is from the northwest.
When the wind is from the south,
I can tell a hawk from a handsaw.
POLONIUS:
Farewell, gentlemen.
Listen, Guildenstern, and you too—
One listener for each ear.
—that child isn't
out of his diapers yet.
He's back in them for the second time,
they say an old man becomes a child again.
I predict he's coming
to tell me about the actors.
You're right, sir, it was Monday morning,
that's when it happened.
POLONIUS:
My lord, I have news for you.
HAMLET:
- When Roscius was an actor in Rome—
- The actors have arrived, my lord.
- Buzz, buzz.
- On my honor—
Then each actor arrived on a donkey.
The best actors in the world, whether
for tragedy, comedy, history, pastoral...
...pastoral-comical, historical-pastoral,
tragical-historical...
...tragical-comical-historical-pastoral,
indivisible scenes, or unlimited poems.
Seneca can't be too serious,
nor Plautus too lighthearted.
For the rules of writing and creativity,
these are the only men.
O Jephthah, judge of Israel,
what a treasure you had.
What treasure did he have, my lord?
Why, "One beautiful daughter and no more,
whom he loved very much."
- Still talking about my daughter.
- Am I not right, old Jephthah?
If you call me Jephthah,
I have a daughter that I love very much.
No, that doesn't follow.
POLONIUS:
What follows then, my lord?
Why, "As by chance, God knows," and then....
You know, "It happened,
just as it was likely to."
The first verse of the pious song
will tell you more...
...because here comes my entertainment.
Welcome, masters, welcome all.
I'm glad to see you well.
Welcome, dear friends.
- Oh, my old friend.
- Sir.
Wow, you've grown a beard
since I last saw you.
Are you here to challenge me
in Denmark, huh?
What, my young lady and mistress.
By the way, you're closer to heaven
than when I last saw you...
...by the height of a platform shoe.
I hope your voice,
like a piece of counterfeit gold...
...isn't cracked.
You're all welcome, everyone.
We'll dive in like French falconers,
going after anything we see.
Let's have a speech right away.
Come on, show us what you've got.
Come on, a passionate speech.
What speech, my good lord?
I remember you gave a speech once,
but it was never performed...
...or if it was, only once.
I remember the play
didn't please the masses.
It was like caviar to the general public.
But it was-- As I understood it...
...and others whose opinions
in these matters were better than mine.
--an excellent play,
well-organized in the scenes...
...written with as much modesty
as skill.
I remember someone said there were no jokes
in the lines to make it entertaining...
...nor any pretentious language...
...that might accuse
the author of being pretentious...
...but called it an honest style...
...as wholesome as it was sweet,
and much more elegant than flashy.
One speech in it I especially loved,
it was Aeneas' tale to Dido...
...and particularly the part
where he talks about Priam's murder.
If you remember it,
start at this line:
Let me see, let me see:
The fierce Pyrrhus,
like the Hyrcanian beast--
- That's not it.
- It starts with Pyrrhus.
It starts with Pyrrhus.
The fierce Pyrrhus,
whose dark armor...
...as black as his intentions,
looked like the night...
...when he lay hidden
in the ominous horse...
...now has this dreadful
and dark appearance smeared...
...with even more dreadful symbols.
- From head to toe, he's now completely red...
ALL: Red.
...horribly covered with the blood of fathers,
mothers, daughters, sons...
...baked and hardened
by the scorching streets...
...that cast a tyrannical and cursed light
on their lord's murder.
Roasted in anger and fire...
...and thus covered
with thickened blood...
...with eyes like glowing stones
the hellish Pyrrhus...
...seeks old grandfather Priam.
So continue.
By God, my lord, well-spoken,
with good accent and good judgment.
Soon he finds him...
...striking too short at the Greeks.
His old sword, too heavy for him,
lies where it falls...
...refusing to follow orders.
An uneven fight,
Pyrrhus charges at Priam...
...and in his anger, misses widely.
But with the gust and force
of his deadly sword...
...the weakened father falls.
Then the city of Troy...
...seems to feel his blow,
with its burning top...
...bends to its foundation,
and with a terrible crash...
...captures Pyrrhus' attention.
For look, his sword,
which was aimed at the white-haired...
...Priam,
seemed to hang in the air.
So like a painted tyrant, Pyrrhus stood...
...and like someone undecided,
did nothing.
But as we often see
before a storm...
...a calm in the sky,
the clouds stop moving...
...the strong winds go silent...
...and the world below is as quiet as death...
...soon the terrifying thunder
tears through the sky.
So after Pyrrhus' pause,
a renewed vengeance drives him to action.
And never did the Cyclops' hammers strike...
...on Mars' armor,
made to last forever...
...with less pity
than Pyrrhus' bloody sword...
...now strikes Priam.
Damn you, fickle Fortune!
All you gods,
in a grand meeting, take away her power...
...break all the spokes and rims
from her wheel...
...and roll the round hub
down the hill of heaven...
...as low as to the demons!
This is too long.
It should go to the barber, along with your beard.
Please, continue.
He's up for a dance or a dirty joke,
or he'll fall asleep.
Continue.
Get to Hecuba.
But who,
Oh who had seen the veiled queen.
Veiled queen.
That's good. "Veiled queen" is good.
Running barefoot back and forth...
...threatening the flames
with blind tears.
A rag on that head
where the crown once was...
...and for a robe,
around her thin and overburdened body...
...a blanket grabbed in fear.
Anyone who saw this,
with a tongue dipped in venom...
...against Fortune's rule
would have spoken treason.
But if the gods themselves
had seen her then...
...when she saw Pyrrhus
cruelly playing...
...by hacking with his sword
her husband's body...
...the immediate outburst of cries
that she made...
...unless mortal things
don't move them at all...
...would have made the burning eyes
of heaven shed tears...
...and stirred passion in the gods.
Look, hasn't he changed color,
and has tears in his eyes.
Please, no more.
[APPLAUDING]
- That's good.
- Sir.
I'll have you finish the rest soon.
Will you make sure the actors are treated well?
Do you hear me? Treat them well...
...because they are the summary
and brief record of the times.
After you die, it's better
to have a bad epitaph...
...than their bad opinion while you're alive.
My lord, I'll treat them
according to what they deserve.
God's body, man, much better.
If you treat everyone based on what they deserve,
who would escape punishment?
Treat them according to your own honor
and dignity.
The less they deserve,
the more credit you get for your generosity.
- Bring them in.
- Come on, gentlemen.
Follow him, friends.
We'll watch a play tomorrow.
Do you hear me, old friend?
- Can you perform The Murder of Gonzago?
- Yes, my lord.
We'll have it tomorrow night.
Could you, if needed, learn a speech
of about a dozen or 16 lines...
...that I would write and add to it,
could you do that?
- Yes, my lord.
- Very well.
Follow that lord,
and make sure you don't mock him.
My good friends, I'll leave you until tonight.
- You're welcome to Elsinore.
- Thank you, my lord.
Yes, so, goodbye.
[PANTING]
Now I'm alone.
Oh, what a villain...
...and lowly slave am I.
Isn't it outrageous
that this actor here...
...just in a pretend scenario...
...in a dream of passion...
...could make himself
believe so much...
...that from his acting
his whole face changed...
...tears in his eyes,
a look of distraction...
...a broken voice...
...and his whole being matching
his imagination?
And all for nothing.
For Hecuba.
What's Hecuba to him, or he to Hecuba,
that he should cry for her?
What would he do if he had the reason
and the trigger for passion that I have?
He would flood the stage with tears...
...and shock everyone
with terrible speech...
...drive the guilty mad
and terrify the innocent...
...confuse the ignorant, and truly amaze
the very senses of sight and sound.
Yet I,
a dull and cowardly rascal...
...daydreaming like a fool,
not thinking about my purpose...
...and can't say anything.
No, not even for a king...
...whose property and very life
have been horribly defeated.
Am I a coward?
Who calls me a villain,
hits me on the head...
...pulls off my beard
and blows it in my face...
...tweaks my nose,
calls me a liar to my face...
...as deeply as to my lungs?
Who does this to me?
Damn it, I should take it!
It must be
that I'm too timid and lack courage...
...to make oppression bitter, or by now...
...I should have fed all the local birds
with this slave's guts.
Bloody, shameless villain!
Remorseless, treacherous,
lustful, heartless villain!
Oh, vengeance!
What a fool am I?
This is so brave...
...that I, the son
of a beloved father who was murdered...
...driven to revenge
by heaven and hell...
...must, like a whore,
express my heart with words...
...and start cursing like a common wench,
a kitchen maid. Shame on it, ugh!
Get to work, my brain.
I've heard
that guilty people watching a play...
...have been so struck by the cleverness of the scene
that immediately...
...they have confessed
their crimes.
For murder, even though it has no voice,
will speak with the most amazing ability.
I'll have these actors perform something
like my father's murder...
...in front of my uncle. I'll watch his reactions,
I'll probe him deeply.
If he even flinches, I'll know what to do.
The ghost I saw
might be the devil...
...and the devil has the power
to take on a pleasing form.
Yes, and maybe,
out of my weakness and sadness—
Since he's very powerful with such spirits.
—he's tricking me...
...to damn me.
I'll need more solid proof than this.
The play's the thing...
...where I'll catch the conscience
of the king.
And can you by no means of conversation...
...find out from him
why he's acting so confused...
...disturbing all his peaceful days
with such wild and dangerous madness?
He does admit
he feels distracted...
...but he won't say
what the cause is.
Nor do we find him willing
to be questioned...
...but with a crafty madness
keeps his distance...
...when we try to get him
to confess...
...his true situation.
- Did he treat you well?
ROSENCRANTZ: Very much like a gentleman.
But with much effort to be friendly.
He asked few questions, but to our inquiries
he was very open in his replies.
Did you offer him any entertainment?
Madam, it happened that some actors
crossed our path on the way.
We told him about them,
and he seemed happy to hear it.
They're around the court, and they've
already been asked to perform for him.
POLONIUS: That's true, and he
asked me to request your majesties...
- ...to watch and listen to the performance.
- Absolutely.
It makes me very happy
to hear he's interested.
Good gentlemen,
encourage him further...
- ...and lead him towards these pleasures.
- We will, my lord.
Sweet Gertrude, please leave us too...
...because we've secretly sent
for Hamlet to come here...
...so that he might, by chance,
meet Ophelia.
Her father and I, as rightful spies,
will position ourselves...
...so that, unseen,
we can honestly judge their meeting...
...and understand from his behavior,
if it's love that's troubling him...
...causing his suffering.
I will do as you say.
And as for you, Ophelia, I hope...
...that your beauty
is the reason for Hamlet's madness.
I hope your virtues
will bring him back to his normal self...
...for both your sakes.
Madam, I hope so too.
POLONIUS:
Ophelia, stay here--
If it pleases you,
we will hide ourselves.
--read this book...
...so it looks like
you're alone for a reason.
We often make this mistake.
It's too often proven that with
a show of devotion and pious actions...
...we cover up evil.
Oh, it's too true.
How that speech
stings my conscience.
The prostitute's cheek,
made beautiful with makeup...
...isn't more ugly
compared to what hides it...
...than my actions
are to my fancy words.
Oh, what a heavy burden.
POLONIUS: I hear him coming.
Let's step back, my lord.
To be, or not to be...
...that's the question:
Is it nobler in the mind
to endure...
...the hardships and misfortunes...
...or to fight back
against a sea of troubles...
...and by opposing, end them?
To die, to sleep.
Nothing more...
...and by sleeping, to say we end...
...the heartache
and the countless natural shocks...
...that flesh is destined to.
It's an outcome
devoutly to be wished for.
To die...
...to sleep.
To sleep...
...maybe to dream.
Yes, there's the catch.
For in that sleep of death...
...what dreams might come...
...when we've left behind
this mortal life...
...must make us pause.
That's the thought
that makes us endure life's hardships for so long.
For who would endure
the beatings and insults of time...
...the oppressor's wrongs,
the arrogance of the proud...
...the pain of unreturned love,
the delays of the law...
...the rudeness of those in power, and the insults
that patient merit receives from the unworthy...
...when he himself could end his troubles
with a simple dagger?
Who would carry burdens...
...to groan and sweat
through a tiring life...
...except for the fear...
...of something after death...
...the undiscovered country...
...from which no traveler returns...
...confuses our will...
...and makes us rather endure
the problems we know...
...than rush to others
that we know nothing about?
So our conscience...
...makes cowards of us all...
...and so the natural color of determination...
...is weakened
by the pale shade of thought...
...and plans
of great importance and significance...
...with this in mind
their paths go astray...
...and lose the name...
...of action.
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
Wait now, the lovely Ophelia.
Nymph...
...in your prayers?
- Will you remember all my sins?
OPHELIA: Good, my lord.
How have you been
all these days?
I humbly thank you.
Well.
My lord...
...I have keepsakes of yours...
...that I've wanted to return for a long time.
Please take them back.
No.
Not me, I never gave you anything.
My honored lord...
...you know very well you did...
...and with them...
...words so sweetly composed
that made the things more valuable.
Their scent is gone...
...take these back.
For to the noble mind, rich gifts
become worthless when the giver is unkind.
There, my lord.
Huh?
- Are you honest?
- My lord?
- Are you beautiful?
- What do you mean, my lord?
That if you are honest and beautiful, your honesty
should not allow any conversation with your beauty.
Can beauty have better dealings
than with honesty?
Honestly, because the power of beauty
will change honesty...
...from what it is to something corrupt more easily than honesty
can change beauty into its own likeness.
This used to be a paradox,
but now time has proven it true.
I did love you once.
Indeed, my lord,
you made me believe that.
Well, you shouldn't have believed me...
...because virtue cannot so change
our nature that we don't still have a taste for it.
I didn't love you.
- I was more deceived.
- Go to a convent.
Why would you want to
give birth to sinners?
I am reasonably honest...
...yet I could accuse myself that it would have been better
if my mother had not given birth to me.
I am proud, vengeful, ambitious, with more
sins than I have thoughts to act them out...
...imagination to shape them,
or time to carry them out.
What should people like me do
crawling between earth and heaven?
We are all complete scoundrels. Trust none of us.
Go to a convent.
[THUD]
Where's your father?
At home, my lord.
Let the doors be shut on him...
...so he can play the fool...
...nowhere but in his own house.
Goodbye.
[CRYING]
Oh, help him, sweet heavens.
If you do marry,
I'll give you this curse as your dowry:
Be as chaste as ice,
as pure as snow...
...you won't escape slander.
Go to a convent, go, goodbye.
Or if you must marry, marry a fool.
Because wise men know well enough
what monsters you make of them.
Go to a convent, and quickly.
Goodbye.
Heavenly powers, restore him.
HAMLET: I've heard about
your makeup too, well enough.
God gave you one face,
and you make yourselves another.
You dance, you walk, and you speak...
...and you give nicknames to God's creatures...
...and you make your flirtation
seem like innocence.
Enough.
I won't have any more of it.
It has driven me mad.
I say...
...we will have...
...no more marriages.
Those who are already married...
...all but one, will live.
The rest will stay as they are.
[SHRIEKS]
To a convent.
Go.
Oh, what a noble mind is ruined here.
The courtier's, soldier's, scholar's eye...
...tongue, sword...
...the hope and pride
of the beautiful state...
...the trendsetter
and the model of form...
...the one everyone watched...
...completely, completely fallen.
And I...
...of all women, most miserable and wretched...
...who enjoyed the sweetness
of his musical promises...
...now see that noble
and most supreme reason...
...like sweet bells clanging,
out of tune and harsh.
That unmatched form and feature
of youthful bloom...
...destroyed by madness.
Oh, woe is me,
to have seen what I have seen...
...and see what I see now.
Love?
His feelings don't lean that way...
...and what he said, though it
was a bit disorganized, wasn't madness.
There's something in his soul
over which his sadness broods...
...and I fear the outcome
will be dangerous.
To prevent this, I have
quickly decided:
He will go to England
to demand our overdue tribute.
Maybe the seas and different countries,
with varied sights...
...will drive out this settled
matter in his heart...
...which his mind keeps dwelling on
and makes him unlike himself.
What do you think of it?
It should work.
But still, I believe
the start and cause of his sadness...
...came from neglected love.
How are you, Ophelia?
You don't need to tell us
what Lord Hamlet said.
We heard it all.
My lord, do as you wish...
...but, if you think it's right, after the play...
...let his mother speak to him alone
to find out his troubles.
Let her be direct with him...
...and I'll be listening
to their entire conversation.
If she doesn't find out,
send him to England...
...or confine him where
you think best.
It will be done.
Madness in important people
must not go unwatched.
Speak the speech, please,
as I taught you:
Smoothly and naturally.
But if you just mouth the words,
like many of your actors do...
...I might as well have the town crier
speak my lines.
And don't wave your hands around too much
like this...
...but be gentle with your movements.
Because in the rush, storm, and
whirlwind of your emotions...
...you need to develop a calmness
that makes it smooth.
Oh, it bothers me deeply to hear
a loud, wig-wearing guy...
...rip a passion to shreds,
making the audience's ears hurt...
...who mostly
can't understand anything...
- ...except for confusing gestures and noise.
- My lord.
I'd have such a person punished
for overacting like Termagant.
- It's more over-the-top than Herod. Please avoid it.
- I promise, sir.
And don't be too dull, either,
but let your own judgment guide you.
Match the action to the word,
and the word to the action...
...with this important note:
Don't go beyond
what is natural.
Because anything overdone
misses the point of acting...
...which was and still is...
...to reflect nature...
...to show virtue its true face,
and mockery its own image...
...and the times we live in
their true form and pressure.
Now, if you overdo it or do it poorly,
even if it makes the unskilled laugh...
...it will only upset the wise.
The opinion of one knowledgeable person
should, in your consideration...
...outweigh a whole theater full of others.
Oh, there are actors
that I've seen perform...
...and heard others praise,
highly, without exaggeration...
...who neither have
the accent of Christians...
...nor the walk of a Christian,
pagan, or human...
...who strutted and shouted so much...
...that I thought some
of nature's apprentices had made humans...
...and hadn't done a good job,
they mimicked humanity so badly.
I hope we've somewhat improved that here.
Oh, fix it completely.
And let those who play the clowns
stick to their lines.
Because there are some
who will laugh themselves...
...to get a few
simple-minded spectators to laugh too...
...even though at the same time
some important part of the play...
...needs to be considered.
That's terrible...
...and shows a pathetic ambition
in the fool who does it.
Go get ready.
How are you, my lord?
Will the king watch this performance?
- And the queen too, and right away.
- Tell the actors to hurry.
Will you two help speed them up?
- We will, my lord.
- Hey, Horatio.
- Here, dear lord, at your service.
Horatio, you're as honest a man
as I've ever met.
- Oh, my dear lord--
- No, don't think I'm flattering you.
Because what advantage
could I gain from you...
...that you have no income except your good spirits
to sustain and dress you?
Why should the poor be praised?
No, let the sweet-talking tongue
flatter ridiculous grandeur...
...and bend the willing knee
in submission...
...where flattery might bring profit.
Do you hear me?
Since my dear soul
had the power to choose...
...and could distinguish between men, her choice
she has chosen you for herself.
For you have been like someone,
enduring everything, yet suffering nothing...
...a man who takes life's blows and rewards
with equal gratitude.
And blessed are those whose emotions
and judgment are so well balanced...
...that they aren't just an instrument
for Fortune's whims...
...to play whatever tune she wants.
Give me a man
who isn't a slave to his emotions...
...and I'll hold him
close to my heart...
...yes, in the core of my heart...
...just like I do with you.
I've said a bit too much about this.
There's a play tonight in front of the king.
One scene is similar to the story
I told you about my father's death.
I ask you, when you see
that scene begin...
...with your very soul
watch my uncle.
If his hidden guilt
doesn't reveal itself in one speech...
...then the ghost we saw
is damned...
...and my thoughts are as dirty
as Vulcan's forge.
Pay close attention to him,
because I'll be watching his face closely...
...and afterward, we'll both share our opinions
on how he seemed.
Okay, my lord.
If he does anything suspicious
while this play is happening...
...and gets away with it...
...I'll take the blame.
They're coming to the play.
I need to act casual. Find a seat.
[APPLAUDING]
How's our cousin Hamlet doing?
Excellent, truly,
like a chameleon's meal.
I eat the air, full of promises.
- You can't feed chickens like that.
- I don't understand this answer, Hamlet.
These words aren't mine.
No, nor mine now.
[PEOPLE LAUGHING]
My lord.
You acted at the university, you say.
Yes, I did, my lord,
and was considered a good actor.
And what role did you play?
- I played Julius Caesar.
- Oh.
I was killed in the Capitol.
Brutus killed me.
It was a cruel act of him
to kill such an important person there.
[LAUGHING]
- Are the actors ready?
- Yes, my lord, they're waiting for you.
Come here, my dear Hamlet. Sit by me.
No, dear mother,
here's something more appealing.
Do you notice that?
- Lady, can I rest my head in your lap?
- No, my lord.
- I mean, can I lay my head on your lap?
- Yes.
- Did you think I meant something inappropriate?
- I wasn't thinking anything.
- A nice thought to be between a woman's legs.
- What is?
- Nothing.
- You're in a good mood, my lord.
Who, me? I'm just your entertainer.
What else can a man do but be happy?
Look how cheerful my mother is,
and my father died just two hours ago.
No, it's been two months, my lord.
That long?
Well then, let the devil wear black,
because I'll wear something fancy.
Wow, he died two months ago
and still not forgotten.
Then there's hope a great man's memory
might last half a year after he's gone.
By the lady, he must build churches then...
...or else he'll be forgotten
like the hobbyhorse...
...whose epitaph is,
"Oh, oh, the hobbyhorse is forgotten."
What does this mean?
This is sneaky mischief.
It means trouble.
It seems this show
explains the plot of the play.
We'll find out from this guy.
The actors can't keep secrets,
they'll reveal everything.
- Will he tell us what this means?
- Any show you'll show him.
Don't be shy to show,
he won't be shy to tell you.
You're naughty, you're naughty.
I'll watch the play.
For us and our tragedy...
...here bowing to your kindness...
...we ask for your patience.
Is this the introduction,
or a ring's inscription?
- It's short, my lord.
- Like a woman's love.
Thirty times the sun's chariot
has gone around...
...the ocean's salty waves...
...and the earth's round ground...
...and 30 dozen moons
with borrowed light...
...around the world
have passed 12 times 30...
...since love united our hearts
and marriage joined our hands...
...in the most sacred bonds.
So many journeys may the sun and moon
make us count again before love ends.
But alas, you have been so unwell lately...
...so far from happiness
and your usual self...
...that I doubt you.
Yet, though I doubt...
...I don't want to upset you, my lord,
it must mean nothing.
For women's fear and love
are either nothing or extreme.
Now you know how my love is,
proof has shown you...
...and as my love is measured, so is my fear.
Where love is great,
the smallest doubts are fears.
Where little fears grow big,
great love grows there.
Honestly, I must leave you, love,
and soon too.
My abilities
have stopped working...
...and you will live
in this beautiful world...
...respected and loved.
And maybe someone as kind
will be your husband--
ACTRESS:
Oh, forget the rest!
Such love must be a betrayal
in my heart.
Let me be cursed with a second husband.
Only those who killed the first
marry a second.
That's bitter, bitter.
The reasons for second marriages
are practical, not out of love.
I kill my first husband again...
...when my second husband
kisses me in bed.
ACTOR: I believe you mean
what you say now...
...but what we decide to do
we often don't follow through.
Intentions are just memories' servants...
...born in a rush but weak...
...like unripe fruit
hanging on the tree...
...but falls easily
when it ripens.
It's crucial that we forget
to repay ourselves what we owe ourselves.
What we decide
in the heat of the moment...
...loses its purpose
when the passion fades.
The intensity of either grief or joy...
...destroys
themselves:
Where joy is at its peak,
grief is most painful.
Grief finds joy, joy finds grief,
on the slightest chance.
[ACTOR GRUNTS]
This world doesn't last forever...
...and it's not surprising...
...that even our loves
change with our fortunes.
For it's still a question to be answered...
...whether love controls fortune
or fortune controls love.
When a great man falls,
you'll see his followers leave.
Poor men who rise
make friends out of enemies.
And so love follows fortune...
...for those who don't need
will never lack friends...
...and those in need
find false friends...
...who quickly become enemies.
But to wrap up where I started...
...our desires and destinies are so opposed
that our plans always fail.
Our thoughts are ours,
but their outcomes are not:
So you might think
you'll never remarry...
...but let those thoughts die
when your first husband does.
ACTRESS: May the earth not
give me food, nor heaven light...
...may fun and rest
be locked away from me day and night...
...may my trust and hope
turn to despair...
...may I find comfort in prison
as my only hope.
Every opposite that ruins
the face of joy...
...may it meet what I wish for
and destroy it...
...both here and beyond
may lasting conflict follow me...
...if, once a widow...
...if I ever become a wife.
What if she breaks it now?
It's a serious promise.
Sweetheart, let me stay here for a bit.
I'm starting to feel tired...
...and I'd like to distract myself...
...from this long day by sleeping.
Sleep, calm your mind...
...and may nothing bad ever happen
between us.
[APPLAUDING]
Madam, what do you think of this play?
- I think the lady protests too much.
- Oh, but she'll stick to her word.
Have you heard the plot?
Is there anything offensive in it?
No, no, they're just joking, poison as a joke.
No offense at all.
- What's the play called?
- The Mousetrap.
Well, how? It's symbolic. This play
shows a murder that happened in Vienna:
Gonzago is the duke's name,
and his wife is Baptista.
You'll see. It's a tricky piece of work.
But so what?
Your Majesty, and we
who have clear consciences, it doesn't affect us.
Let the guilty squirm,
we're not bothered.
This is Lucianus,
the king's nephew.
You're as good as a narrator.
I could interpret between you and your love
if I could see the actors.
- You're sharp, my lord.
- It took some effort to dull my edge.
- Still better, and worse.
- That's how you confuse your husbands.
Start, murderer!
Stop making those awful faces and start.
Come on. The croaking raven
calls for revenge.
Dark thoughts, ready hands...
...perfect drugs, and the right time...
...all coming together,
with no one else seeing.
You vile mix
of midnight herbs gathered...
...with Hecate's curse
thrice cast, thrice infected...
...your natural magic and terrible power...
...take over healthy life immediately.
He poisons him in the garden
for his wealth.
His name is Gonzago.
The story is well-known,
and written in excellent Italian.
You'll soon see how the murderer
wins the love of Gonzago's wife!
[GASPS]
OPHELIA:
The king is getting up.
What, scared by a fake fire?
- How is my lord doing?
- Stop the play.
Give me some light.
Let's go.
GUARD:
Lights, lights, lights!
HAMLET:
Horatio!
Well, let the wounded deer cry...
...while the unhurt one plays...
...because some must stay awake,
while others must sleep...
...and so the world goes on.
Wouldn't this, sir, and a bunch of fancy feathers,
if my luck changes...
...with two fancy roses
on my worn-out shoes...
...get me a spot in a group of actors?
- Half a share.
- A full one, I say.
You know, dear Damon...
...this kingdom was stripped
of Jove himself...
...and now a real show-off rules here.
a very, very peacock.
You could have made it rhyme.
Oh, good Horatio, I'll trust the ghost's word
for a thousand pounds.
- Did you notice?
- Yes, very well, my lord.
During the talk about the poisoning?
I watched him closely.
Ah.
Come on, let's have some music, bring the recorders.
Because if the king doesn't like the play,
then he just doesn't like it, indeed.
Come on, let's have some music.
- Can I have a word with you?
- A whole story.
- The king, sir--
- What's up with him?
Is in his room
very upset.
- From drinking, sir?
- No, more like anger.
You should let
his doctor know about this.
Because if I try to calm him down
it might just make him angrier.
Get your thoughts organized,
and don't stray so far from my issue.
I'm calm, sir. Go ahead.
The queen, your mother, is very
upset and has sent me to you.
- You're welcome.
- No, this isn't the right kind of courtesy.
If you give me a proper answer,
I'll do what your mother asked.
If not, I'll just leave
and that'll be it.
But, sir, I can't.
- What, my lord?
- Give you a proper answer.
My mind's not well.
But, sir, whatever answer I can give,
you shall have...
...or rather, as you say, my mother will.
So let's get to the point.
My mother, you say?
Then this is what she says:
Your behavior has left her
amazed and in awe.
Oh, wonderful son,
who can so surprise a mother.
But is there more to follow
this mother's amazement? Tell me.
She wants to speak with you
in her room before you go to bed.
We'll obey,
even if she were 10 times our mother.
Do you have any other business with us?
- My lord, you once loved me.
- And I still do, by these hands.
Good my lord,
what's causing your upset?
You lock yourself away
if you don't share your troubles with friends.
Sir, I lack opportunities.
How can that be when the king himself
supports you for the throne?
Yes, sir, but "while the grass grows...."
The saying is a bit old.
[RECORDERS PLAYING]
The recorders. Let me see one.
Why are you trying to
get the upper hand on me...
...as if you want to trap me?
Oh my lord, if I'm being too forward,
it's because I care too much.
I don't really understand that.
Will you play this flute?
- My lord, I can't.
- Please.
- Honestly, I can't.
- I'm asking you.
HORATIO: I don't know how to play it, my lord.
- It's as easy as lying.
Just cover these holes
with your fingers and thumb.
Blow into it and it will play
beautiful music. These are the keys.
But I can't make it produce
any music. I don't have the skill.
Look at you, trying to make me
feel unworthy.
You want to play me,
you pretend to know my secrets...
...you want to uncover
my mysteries...
...you want to explore me from my lowest point
to my highest.
And there's so much music,
such a great voice in this little instrument...
...yet you can't make it speak.
'Sblood, do you think I'm easier
to manipulate than a flute?
Well, call me whatever instrument you want,
even if you can annoy me...
...you can't play me.
- God bless you, sir.
- My lord, the queen wants to speak with you.
Do you see that cloud over there
that's almost shaped like a camel?
By God, it does look like a camel.
- It looks like a weasel.
- With a back like a weasel.
- Or like a whale.
- Very much like a whale.
Then I'll go see my mother soon.
They're pushing me to my limits.
I'll go soon.
- I'll tell her that.
- "Soon" is easy to say.
Leave me, friends.
I don't like him, and it's not safe for us
to let his madness continue.
So get ready.
I'll send your orders right away,
and you'll take him to England with you.
Our situation
can't handle...
...such a dangerous risk as his madness
keeps growing.
We'll take care of it ourselves.
It's a holy and important duty
to keep all those people safe...
...who live and depend on Your Majesty.
An individual's life is protected
by all the strength and defenses of the mind...
...to keep itself safe.
But even more so...
...the spirit on which
many lives depend...
...must be protected.
The fall of a king doesn't happen alone...
...but like a whirlpool, it pulls
everything nearby with it.
It's like a massive wheel
on top of the highest mountain...
...with thousands of
smaller things attached to it...
...which, when it falls...
...every small attachment,
every little consequence...
...gets caught in the chaotic destruction.
The king never sighs alone,
but with a collective groan.
Arm yourself, please,
for this quick journey...
...because we will put restraints on this fear
that is currently too free.
- We'll hurry.
- My lord.
POLONIUS:
He's going to his mother's room.
I'll hide behind the curtain
to listen in.
I'm sure she'll confront him directly.
And, as you said—And it was wisely said.
—it's appropriate that someone else
besides his mother...
...since mothers are naturally biased,
should overhear the conversation.
Goodbye, my king.
I'll check in before you go to bed,
and tell you what I find out.
Thanks, dear lord.
It's now
the very witching hour of night...
...when graveyards open,
and hell itself breathes out...
...its poison into the world.
Now I could drink hot blood...
...and do such terrible deeds that daylight
would be afraid to see them.
Calm down, now to my mother.
Oh heart, don't lose your nature.
Don't let
the spirit of Nero enter this strong heart.
Let me be harsh, but not inhuman.
I'll speak sharply to her, but won't harm her.
My words and soul...
...will be hypocrites in this.
No matter how harshly I speak to her...
...I will never let my soul
agree to act on it.
Oh, my crime is foul.
It reeks to heaven.
It has the oldest curse on it...
...a brother's murder.
I can't pray.
Even though I want to as much as I can...
...my stronger guilt
defeats my strong intention.
And like a man with two tasks,
I hesitate on where to start...
...and end up doing neither.
What if this cursed hand were covered
with my brother's blood...
...isn't there enough rain
in the sweet heavens...
...to wash it white as snow?
What is mercy for
if not to face the face of sin?
And what's prayer but this double power,
to prevent us from falling...
...or to forgive us when we're down?
Then I'll look up.
My sin is done.
But, oh, what kind of prayer
can help me now?
"Forgive me my terrible murder"?
That can't be...
...since I still have
the things I killed for:
My crown, my ambition...
...and my queen.
Can someone be forgiven
and keep the crime?
In the corrupt ways of this world...
...a guilty person's wealth
can sometimes bypass justice...
...and often we see that the wicked gains
can buy their way out of the law.
But it's not like that in heaven.
There's no trickery there...
...where actions are seen
for what they truly are...
...and we are forced...
...to face
the full extent of our faults...
...and give evidence against ourselves.
What now? What's left to do?
Try to see what repentance can achieve.
What can't it do?
But what can it do if one can't repent?
Oh, miserable state,
Oh heart as dark as death...
...Oh trapped soul that struggles to be free
but gets more entangled.
Help, angels.
Give it a try.
Bend, stubborn knees.
And heart with strings of steel,
be as soft as a newborn baby's sinews.
Maybe everything will be okay.
HAMLET:
Now I could do it easily...
...now that he's praying.
And now I'll do it.
And then he goes to heaven...
...and that's my revenge.
[BLOOD SPLATTERS]
HAMLET:
I need to think this through.
A villain kills my father, and for that...
...I, his only son, send this same villain
to heaven.
Oh, that's a reward, not revenge.
He killed my father without warning, full of life...
...with all his sins in full bloom,
as fresh as spring.
And how he stands in judgment,
only heaven knows.
But from what we see
and how we think...
...he's in deep trouble.
And am I really avenged
if I kill him while he's cleansing his soul...
...when he's ready and prepared
for his journey?
No.
Put away the sword,
and wait for a worse moment.
When he's drunk and asleep...
...or in a fit of rage...
...or in the sinful pleasure
of his bed...
...gambling, swearing, or doing something
that has no hint of salvation...
...then strike him,
so his heels kick towards heaven...
...and his soul
is as damned and dark...
...as the hell where it's headed.
My mother is waiting.
This delay just prolongs your sickly days.
My words fly up,
but my thoughts stay below.
Words without thoughts
never reach heaven.
He'll come straight here.
Make sure you confront him.
Tell him his antics
have been too outrageous to tolerate...
...and your grace shielded him
and protected him from a lot of trouble.
I'll keep quiet here.
Please be direct with him.
- I promise. Don't worry about me.
HAMLET: Mother, Mother, Mother!
Step back, I hear him coming.
Now, Mother, what's going on?
Hamlet,
you've really upset your father.
Mother,
you've really upset my father.
- You're answering with nonsense.
- You're asking with a wicked tone.
- What's going on?
- What's happening now?
- Have you forgotten me?
- No, I swear, I haven't.
You are the queen,
your husband's brother's wife.
And I wish it weren't true,
you are my mother.
Well then,
I'll call in someone who can speak to you.
Come on, sit down.
You're not going anywhere.
You're not leaving until I hold up a mirror
so you can see your true self.
What are you going to do?
You're not going to kill me, are you?
- Help, oh!
HAMLET: What, oh! Help!
POLONIUS: Help, help!
HAMLET: What, a rat?
- Dead, for a coin, dead!
POLONIUS: Ow! Ow!
[SHOUTING AND GRUNTING]
I've been killed.
GERTRUDE:
Oh my, what have you done?
I don't know. Is it the king?
Oh, what a reckless and bloody act this is.
Almost as bad, dear mother,
as killing a king and marrying his brother.
- Killing a king?
- Yes, ma'am, that's what I said.
You foolish, reckless, intrusive fool.
Goodbye.
I thought you were someone better.
Accept your fate.
Being too nosy
can be dangerous.
Stop wringing your hands. Calm down!
Sit down,
and let me break your heart.
Because I will,
if it's made of anything that can feel...
...if bad habits haven't made it so tough
that it can't sense anything.
What have I done,
that you dare speak to me...
...in such a rude way?
Such an act
that ruins modesty...
...calls virtue a lie, takes the beauty
from innocent love...
...and leaves a scar...
...makes marriage vows
as false as a gambler's promises.
Oh, such a deed
that takes the soul out of commitment...
...and turns sweet religion into
just a bunch of words.
Heaven's face glows,
yes, this solid and massive world...
...with a sad look, as if facing judgment,
is sickened by the act.
Oh my, what act is so loud
and dramatic?
Look at this picture,
and at this one...
...the fake representation
of two brothers.
See what grace was on this face.
The curls of Hyperion,
the forehead of Jove himself...
...an eye like Mars,
to intimidate and lead...
...a presence like the messenger Mercury
newly arrived on a sky-high hill.
A combination and a form indeed
where every god seemed to put their mark...
...to assure the world of a true man.
This was your husband.
Now look at what comes next.
Here is your husband...
...like a diseased ear,
ruining his good brother.
Do you have eyes?
Could you leave this beautiful mountain
to feed and thrive on this barren land?
Do you have eyes?
You can't call it love, because at your age
the wildness in your blood has calmed...
...it's modest,
and listens to reason.
And what kind of judgment
would go from this to that?
You have sense,
otherwise you couldn't move.
But surely that sense is paralyzed.
For madness wouldn't make such a mistake...
...nor was sense ever so overwhelmed
that it didn't keep some ability to choose...
...to decide between such differences.
What devil was it that
tricked you in blind man's bluff?
Eyes without feeling,
feeling without sight...
...ears without hands or eyes,
smelling without any...
...or just a weak part of one true sense
couldn't be so confused.
Oh shame...
...where is your blush?
Rebellious hell,
if you can stir in a woman's bones...
...let virtue in fiery youth be like wax
and melt in its own fire.
Don't declare shame...
...when the overpowering passion
takes control...
...since even frost burns actively,
and reason serves desire.
Oh, Hamlet, stop speaking.
You turn my eyes into my very soul...
...and there I see
such dark and deep stains...
...that won't wash away.
No, but to live
in the sweaty filth of a stained bed...
...stewed in corruption, sweetening
and making love over the disgusting mess!
Oh, stop speaking to me!
These words pierce my ears like daggers.
No more, dear Hamlet.
A murderer and a villain...
...a servant not worth a twentieth
of your previous lord, a mockery of kings...
...a thief of the empire and the rule...
...who stole the precious crown
from a shelf and put it in his pocket.
- No more.
- A king of rags and patches.
Save me...
...and protect me with your wings,
you heavenly guards.
What does your noble form want?
Alas, he's mad.
Aren't you here
to scold your slow son...
...who, lost in time and emotion,
lets slip by...
...the important task
of your fearful command?
Oh, speak.
[WHISPERS]
Don't forget.
This visit is just to sharpen...
...your almost dulled purpose.
But look...
...your mother is in shock.
Step between her and her troubled soul.
Imagination in the weakest bodies...
...works the strongest.
Talk to her, Hamlet.
How are you, my lady?
Oh, what's wrong with you...
...that you stare
at nothing...
...and talk
to thin air?
Your eyes
show your wild thoughts.
Like soldiers waking up
to an alarm...
...your hair stands on end,
like it's alive.
Oh, dear son...
...in your heated state,
calm down.
What are you looking at?
At him.
See how pale he looks.
His form and purpose together,
preaching to stones...
...would make them understand.
Don't look at me...
...or your sad expression will change
my harsh intentions.
Then what I need to do
will lose its true meaning.
Tears might replace blood.
- Who are you talking to?
- Do you see anything there?
Nothing at all, yet I see everything.
- Did you hear anything?
- Just us.
Look there! See how it slips away!
My father, dressed as he was in life!
Look, there he goes, right now,
out the door.
This is just your imagination.
This creation without a body
is what madness is good at.
Madness.
My pulse, like yours,
beats steadily...
...and sounds healthy.
What I said isn't madness.
Test me,
and I'll repeat it...
...which madness would avoid.
Mother, for the love of grace...
...don't flatter yourself
by thinking...
...that it's my madness speaking,
not your wrongdoing.
It will just cover up
the sore spot...
...while hidden corruption inside
spreads unnoticed.
Confess to heaven.
Repent for the past,
avoid what's coming...
...and don't spread
fertilizer on the weeds...
...to make them grow worse.
Forgive me for my virtue...
...because in these indulgent times
even virtue has to ask vice for forgiveness...
...yes, restrain and persuade
to do something good for him.
Oh, Hamlet.
You've broken my heart in two.
Throw away the worse part of it,
and live with the better half.
Good night.
But don't go to my uncle's bed.
Pretend to have a virtue if you don't.
That habit,
which destroys all sense...
...of the devil's habits, is still an angel in this...
...because it can make good actions
seem natural...
...when put on properly.
Hold back tonight,
and it will make it easier...
...to abstain next time.
The next time will be easier.
Because practice can almost change
your natural tendencies...
...and either shame the devil...
...or get rid of him
with great power.
Once more, good night.
And when you want to be blessed...
...I'll ask for your blessing.
I regret what happened to this lord.
But heaven has decided
to punish me with this, and this with me...
...so I must be their instrument
and servant.
I will take care of him...
...and will justify
the death I caused him.
So again, good night.
I have to be cruel to be kind.
This is the start of the bad...
...and worse is yet to come.
One more thing, good lady.
What should I do?
Not this, by any means, that I ask you to do:
Let the bloated king
tempt you back to bed...
...playfully pinch your cheek...
...call you his pet, and let him,
for a couple of dirty kisses...
...or touching your neck
with his cursed fingers...
...make you reveal everything,
that I'm not truly mad...
...but pretending.
It would be good if you let him know.
For who, being a queen,
beautiful, sober, wise...
...would hide such important things
from a toad, a bat, a cat...
...like these?
Who would do that? No...
...despite common sense and secrecy...
...open the basket on the roof...
...let the birds fly,
and like the famous ape...
...try to figure things out
by climbing into the basket...
...and end up breaking your own neck.
Be assured...
...if words are made of breath...
...and breath is life...
...I have no life to breathe
what you've said to me.
I have to go to England, you know that?
Oh, I forgot.
That's been decided.
There are letters sealed.
And my two school friends...
...who I trust
as much as I trust venomous snakes...
...they're carrying the orders.
They have to clear my path
and lead me into trouble.
Let it happen.
It's fun to see the engineer
blown up by his own bomb.
And it will be tough...
...but I'll dig one yard
below their traps...
...and blow them to the moon.
Oh, it's so satisfying
when two schemes collide perfectly.
This man will get me moving.
I'll drag the body into the next room.
Good night, Mother.
This advisor is now very quiet...
...very secretive, and very serious...
...who in life
was a foolish, chattering fool.
Come on, sir...
...let's wrap things up with you.
Good night, Mother.
[CRYING]
CLAUDIUS: There's meaning in
these sighs, these deep breaths...
...you must explain them.
We need to understand them.
- Where is your son?
- Give us some privacy for a moment.
Oh, my lord,
what I've seen tonight.
What, Gertrude? How is Hamlet?
As mad as the sea and wind
when they fight to see which is stronger.
In his crazed state...
...behind the curtain
hearing something move...
...he pulls out his sword...
...shouts, "A rat, a rat!"...
...and in his wild imagination kills...
...the unseen good old man.
Oh, what a terrible act.
It would have been us...
...if we had been there.
His freedom is a threat to everyone.
To you, to us, to everyone.
Oh no, how will this bloody act
be dealt with?
It will be blamed on us, whose duty
was to keep this mad young man
under control and away from people.
But we loved him so much...
...we refused to see
what was necessary...
...like someone who owns a terrible disease...
...to keep it from being revealed, let it consume
even the essence of life.
Where did he go?
To separate the body he has killed...
...over which his very madness...
...like some ore
among a bunch of worthless metals...
...shows itself pure.
- He's crying over what happened.
- Oh Gertrude, let's go.
The sun will touch the mountains
but we'll send him away.
And this horrible act...
...we must with all our authority and skill
both support and justify.
Guildenstern. Friends,
go join up with some more help.
Hamlet, in his madness, has killed Polonius...
...and from his mother's room
dragged him.
Go find him, speak kindly,
and take the body to the chapel.
Please hurry with this.
Come, Gertrude.
We'll call our wisest friends...
...and let them know
both what we plan to do...
...and what's happened unexpectedly.
So envious slander,
whose whisper across the world...
...as straight as a cannon to its target,
sends its poisoned shot...
...may miss our name
and hit the harmless air.
Oh, let's go.
My soul is full of chaos and worry.
[SCREAMING]
- Safely hidden.
GUARD 1: Hamlet, Lord Hamlet!
Wait, what's that noise?
- Who's calling for Hamlet?
GUARD 2: Lord Hamlet!
Oh, here they come.
- What did you do with the dead body?
- Mixed it with dust, where it belongs.
- Tell us where it is, so we can move it.
- Don't believe it.
- Believe what?
- That I can keep your secret.
Besides, to be questioned by a sponge.
What answer should be given
by the son of a king?
Do you take me for a sponge, my lord?
That soaks up the king's favor,
his rewards, his powers.
But such people do the king
the best service in the end.
He keeps them, like a monkey
keeps an apple in the corner of his mouth...
...first tasted to be last eaten.
When he needs what you've gathered...
...he just squeezes you,
and, sponge, you'll be dry again.
I don't understand you, my lord.
I'm glad about that.
A tricky speech falls on a foolish ear.
Tell us where the body is,
and come with us to the king.
The body is with the king, but the king
is not with the body. The king is a thing--
A thing, my lord?
Of nothing. Take me to him.
OPHELIA:
My lord!
Hide and seek, all after.
OPHELIA:
My lord!
My dear Lord Hamlet!
[GLASS SHATTERING]
Hamlet!
[PEOPLE SHOUTING]
GUARD 1:
Hamlet!
[SIGHS]
[GUN COCKS]
I've sent people to find him,
and to locate the body.
It's dangerous
for this man to be free.
But we can't
use the full force of the law on him.
He's loved by the confused masses...
...who judge not with their minds,
but with their eyes...
...and when that's the case...
...the punishment is considered,
but not the crime.
To keep everything calm and smooth...
...sending him away suddenly must seem
like a planned delay.
Desperate diseases...
...are treated with desperate measures,
or not at all.
[DOOR OPENS]
What's happened now?
We can't get him to tell us
where the body is hidden.
- Where is he?
- Outside, under guard, waiting for your orders.
- Bring him to us.
- Hey, Guildenstern.
Bring in my lord.
- Now, Hamlet, where's Polonius?
- At dinner.
At dinner? Where?
Not where he's eating, but where he's being eaten.
A certain gathering of political worms
is already at him.
Your worm is the only true emperor of diet.
We fatten all creatures to fatten ourselves,
and we fatten ourselves for maggots.
Your fat king and your skinny beggar
are just different courses:
Two dishes, but at the same table.
- That's the end.
- Oh no, oh no.
A man can fish with the worm
that ate a king...
...and eat the fish
that fed on that worm.
- What do you mean?
- Nothing...
...just to show you how a king can
travel through the guts of a beggar.
Where is Polonius?
In heaven. Send someone to check.
If your messenger doesn't find him there...
...look for him in the other place yourself.
But if you don't find him
within a month...
...you'll smell him
as you go up the stairs into the lobby.
Go look for him there.
He'll wait for you to come.
Hamlet, because of what you've done,
for your own safety--
Which we care about as much as we grieve
for what you've done.
--we must send you away
very quickly.
So get ready.
The ship is ready, and the wind is favorable...
...and everything is set for England.
- For England?
- Yes, Hamlet.
- Good.
- It would be if you knew our plans.
I see an angel who knows them.
But come on, to England.
Goodbye, dear mother.
- Your loving father, Hamlet.
- Mother.
Father and mother are husband and wife...
...husband and wife are one...
...so she is my mother.
Come...
...to England.
Wait.
[GRUNTING]
Follow him. Get him on the ship quickly.
I'll send him off tonight.
Go. Everything is ready and done
that depends on the matter.
Please, hurry.
And England...
...if you value my friendship at all--
My great power should make you understand
since your wound still looks fresh and red...
...from the Danish sword,
and your respect pays homage to us.
--you must not ignore
our royal command...
...which fully means,
as stated in the letters...
...the immediate death of Hamlet!
Do it, England.
For like a fever in my blood he rages...
...and you must cure me.
Until I know it's done...
...whatever my fate,
my happiness hasn't started.
[OPHELIA SCREAMING]
Go, captain.
Give my regards to the Danish king.
Tell him that with his permission, Fortinbras
requests passage...
...for a promised march through his kingdom.
You know the meeting point.
If his majesty needs anything from us...
...we'll show our respect in person...
...and let him know.
- I'll do it, my lord.
- Go...
...quietly.
HAMLET:
Good sir, whose troops are these?
They are Norway's, sir.
What is their purpose, sir, please?
Against a part of Poland.
- Who leads them, sir?
- The nephew of Old Norway, Fortinbras.
Is it against the heart of Poland, sir,
or just a border area?
Honestly speaking...
...with no exaggeration...
...we're going to capture a small piece of land
that has no value except for its name.
To pay 5 ducats, 5...
...I wouldn't even rent it.
Nor will it be given to Norway or the Pole
for a higher price if it were sold outright.
Then the Poles will never defend it.
Yes, it's already guarded.
Two thousand people
and 20,000 ducats...
...won't even consider
the question of this trivial matter.
This is the infection
of too much wealth and peace...
...that breaks inside...
...and shows no outward reason
why the person dies.
Thank you kindly, sir.
Goodbye, sir.
- Would you like to go, my lord?
- I'll be with you shortly.
Go on ahead a bit.
How every situation
seems to work against me...
...and push my slow revenge.
What is a person...
...if their main purpose and use of time
is just to sleep and eat?
Just an animal, nothing more.
Surely, the one who made us
with such broad thinking...
...looking at the past and future...
...didn't give us
that capability and godlike reason...
...to sit unused within us.
Now, whether it's animal-like forgetfulness...
...or some cowardly hesitation
of thinking too much about the outcome--
A thought which, divided...
...has only one part wisdom
and three parts cowardice.
--I don't know...
...why I still live to say
this thing needs doing...
...since I have cause and desire
and strength and means to do it.
Obvious examples as clear as day urge me:
Look at this army
of such size and expense...
...led by a delicate and gentle prince...
...whose spirit,
filled with divine ambition...
...mocks the uncertain future...
...risking what is mortal and unsure...
...to all that fortune, death,
and danger dare...
...even for something as small as an eggshell.
To truly be great
is not to act without a significant reason...
...but to find a reason in something small
when honor is at stake.
So how do I stand,
with a father killed...
...a mother dishonored...
...reasons of my mind
and my emotions...
...and let it all rest...
...while to my shame...
...I see the impending death
of 20,000 men...
...who, for a fantasy and a trick of fame...
...go to their graves like they're going to bed...
...fighting for a piece of land where the numbers
can't even test the cause...
...which isn't even enough space
and area...
...to bury the dead?
Oh, from this moment on...
...my thoughts must be violent...
...or they're worthless.
CLAUDIUS: When troubles come,
they don't come one at a time...
...but all at once.
First, her father was killed.
Then, your son disappeared...
...and he was the main cause
of his own rightful departure.
The people are confused,
their thoughts are troubled...
...and they're whispering about good Polonius' death.
And we handled it poorly
by burying him in secret.
Poor Ophelia...
...is torn apart
and lost her good judgment...
...without which we're just images
or mere animals.
Finally, and just as significant as all this,
her brother secretly came back from France...
...and is intrigued by all this,
staying hidden.
He doesn't lack people to fill his ears with
harmful talk about his father's death.
In this situation, lacking facts...
...they won't hesitate to accuse us
in whispers.
Oh my dear Gertrude, this,
like a deadly weapon...
...in many ways
is killing me over and over.
[OPHELIA GRUNTING]
I won't talk to her.
She's persistent, clearly disturbed.
- Her condition deserves sympathy.
- What does she want?
She talks a lot about her father...
...says she hears
there's deceit in the world...
...and sighs, and clutches her chest.
She angrily kicks at nothing...
...says things uncertainly
that only make partial sense.
Her words mean nothing...
...yet the way she uses them makes
people try to make sense of it.
They guess at it...
...and piece together her words
to fit their own ideas...
...which, as her winks and nods
and gestures suggest...
...might make someone think
there could be meaning...
...though nothing is certain,
yet much is sadly implied.
It would be good to talk to her...
...because she might spread
dangerous ideas in impressionable minds.
Let her come in.
[GERTRUDE SIGHING]
To my troubled soul, as sin's true nature is...
...every little thing seems to lead
to something terrible.
Guilt is so full of clumsy jealousy,
it reveals itself by trying to hide.
OPHELIA: Where is the beautiful majesty
of Denmark?
What's going on, Ophelia?
How can I recognize your true love
from someone else?
By his cockle hat and staff,
and his sandals.
Oh dear lady,
what does this song mean?
What do you say?
No...
[OPHELIA CRYING]
...please, listen.
He's dead and gone, ma'am
He's dead and gone
At his head, there's a green grass turf
At his feet, a stone
GERTRUDE:
No, but Ophelia--
OPHELIA:
Please, listen.
His shroud is as white as mountain snow
GERTRUDE:
Oh no, look here, my lord.
Covered with sweet flowers
Which didn't go to the grave
With true love's tears
How are you, dear lady?
Well, thank you.
They say the owl
was a baker's daughter.
Lord, we know who we are,
but not what we might become.
May God be with you.
She's thinking about her father.
[SCREAMING]
Please!
Let's not talk about this!
But when they ask you what it means...
...tell them this:
[SINGING]
Tomorrow is Valentine's Day
Early in the morning,
And I, a maid, at your window
To be your Valentine
Then he got up and dressed
And opened the chamber door
Let in the maid, who left
Never a maid anymore
- Sweet Ophelia.
- Really?
Without swearing, I'll finish it.
By Jesus and Saint Charity
Oh, what a shame
Young men will do it if they get the chance
By God, they are to blame
She said:
"Before you slept with me,
you promised to marry me
And I would have, by the sun,
if you hadn't come to my bed"
[CRYING]
How long has she been like this?
I hope everything will be okay.
OPHELIA:
We must be patient.
But I can't help but cry...
...thinking they laid him
in the cold ground.
My brother will hear about it.
[OPHELIA GASPING]
And so I thank you
for your good advice!
Come...
[OPHELIA SNIFFS]
...my carriage!
Good night, ladies.
Good night, sweet ladies, good night.
Good night, sweet ladies!
- Good night!
- Stay close to her.
OPHELIA: Good night!
CLAUDIUS: Keep a close watch on her, please.
Oh, this is the poison of deep sorrow.
It's all because of her father's death.
And now, look.
CLAUDIUS:
Oh Gertrude, Gertrude.
[MEN SHOUTING]
GERTRUDE:
What's that noise?
Where are my guards? Secure the door.
- What's going on?
- Save yourself, my lord.
The ocean, overflowing its boundaries,
doesn't consume the shores more quickly...
...than young Laertes, in a wild frenzy,
overpowers your officers.
The crowd calls him lord,
and as if the world were just beginning...
...forgetting the past, ignoring tradition...
...the supporters of every word...
...they shout, "Let's choose!
Laertes should be king."
Hats, hands, and voices
cheer it to the skies:
"Laertes should be king. Laertes, king."
How eagerly they follow a false lead!
Oh, this is wrong, you deceitful Danish dogs!
CLAUDIUS:
The doors are broken.
[GERTRUDE SHRIEKS]
Where is this king?
- Gentlemen, stay outside.
- No, let's go in.
- Please, let me speak.
MAN: We will.
Thank you.
LAERTES:
Guard the door!
Oh, you vile king, give me my father!
Calm down, good Laertes.
If I stay calm,
it means I'm not my father's son...
...it dishonors my father...
...it brands my mother...
...even though she is pure and innocent.
What makes you so rebellious, Laertes?
Let him go, Gertrude.
Don't worry about me.
There's a divine protection around a king...
...that treason can only glimpse
at what it wants, achieving little.
Tell me, Laertes,
why are you so angry?
Let him go, Gertrude.
- Speak up, man.
- Where is my father?
- Dead.
GERTRUDE: But not by him.
Let him ask all he wants.
How did he die?
I won't be tricked.
To hell with loyalty.
Vows to the darkest devil.
Conscience and grace
to the deepest pit.
I dare to face damnation.
I'm determined...
...to neglect both worlds,
let whatever happens, happen.
I will only seek revenge
completely for my father.
- Who will stop you?
- My determination, not the whole world.
And for my resources...
...I'll manage them so well
they'll last a long time.
Good Laertes...
...if you want to know for sure
about your dear father's death...
...is it written in your revenge that,
all or nothing...
...you'll involve both friends and enemies,
winners and losers?
- Only his enemies.
- Will you recognize them, then?
To his good friends, I'll open
my arms wide...
...and like the generous pelican,
I'll nourish them with my blood.
Now you're talking
like a good child and a true gentleman.
[GERTRUDE PANTING]
That I'm innocent
of your father's death...
...and deeply grieving for it...
...will become as clear to you
as daylight is to your eyes.
[OPHELIA SHOUTING]
HORATIO:
Let her in.
LAERTES:
What's that noise?
[OPHELIA GASPING]
Oh, heat, dry up my brains.
Tears, seven times saltier,
burn out the sense and virtue of my eyes.
[OPHELIA GIGGLING]
LAERTES: By heaven, your madness
will be paid back in full...
...until the scales tip.
LAERTES:
Oh, May's rose, dear girl...
...kind sister, sweet Ophelia.
Oh heavens...
...is it possible a young girl's mind
can be as fragile as an old man's life?
Love refines nature,
and when it's refined...
...it sends some precious part
of itself...
...after the thing it loves.
They carried him uncovered on the bier
[SINGING AND LAUGHING]
Hey, non nony, nony, hey, nony
And many tears fell on his grave
Goodbye, my dove.
If you had your wits
and urged revenge...
...it couldn't move like this.
You must sing:
Down, a-down, a-down, a-down
And you, call him:
A-down, a-down, a-down
Oh, how the wheel suits it.
It was the dishonest steward
who stole his master's daughter.
[OPHELIA SHUSHES]
This nonsense means more than sense.
Here's rosemary,
that's for remembering.
Please, love, remember.
And here are pansies, that's for thoughts.
A lesson in madness...
...thoughts and remembrance combined.
Here's fennel for you...
...and columbines.
Here's rue for you,
and here's some for me.
We can call it herb of grace on Sundays.
OPHELIA: Oh, you should wear your rue
differently.
Here's a daisy.
OPHELIA:
I would have given you some violets...
...but they all died
when my father passed away.
OPHELIA:
They say he died well.
[SINGING]
For lovely sweet robin is all my joy
Thoughts and suffering,
passion, even hell itself...
...she turns into charm and beauty.
And will he not come back?
No, no, he's dead
Go to your deathbed
He will never come back
His beard was white as snow
His hair was all flaxen
He's gone, he's gone
And we let go of our sorrow
God have mercy on his soul
And on all Christian souls...
...I pray to God.
Goodbye.
[SOBBING]
Do you see this, O God?
Laertes, I need to share in your grief,
or you're denying me my right.
Go aside, choose whoever
your wisest friends are...
...and they will listen
and judge between you and me.
If they find us guilty
by direct or indirect means...
...we will give you our kingdom, our crown,
our life, and everything we own...
...to satisfy you.
But if not, please be patient with us...
...and we will work together with you
to bring you peace.
Let it be so.
The way he died...
...his secret burial—
No memorial, sword,
or emblem over his grave...
...no noble ceremony or formal display.
—cry out to be heard,
as if from heaven to earth...
...that I must question it.
So you will.
And where the crime is,
let justice be served.
Please, come with me.
HORATIO:
Who are they that want to speak with me?
Sailors, sir.
They say they have letters for you.
[WATER SPLASHING
AND OPHELIA SCREAMING]
I don't know from which part of the world
I should expect a message if not from Lord Hamlet.
MAN: God bless you.
- May He bless you too.
He will, sir, if it pleases Him.
Here's a letter for you, sir.
It's from the ambassador
who was headed to England...
...if your name is Horatio,
as I believe it is.
"Horatio, when you have
read this...
...give these men some way
to reach the king. They have letters for him.
Before we were two days at sea...
...a pirate ship fully armed for battle
chased us.
Realizing we were too slow...
...we summoned forced bravery,
and during the fight, I boarded their ship.
They quickly got away from our ship,
leaving me as their only prisoner.
They treated me
like merciful thieves...
...but they knew what they were doing:
I'm supposed to do them a favor.
Make sure the king gets the letters
I sent...
...and come to me as fast
as if you were fleeing death.
I have things to tell you
that will leave you speechless...
...though they are too trivial
for the seriousness of the situation.
These good people
will bring you to where I am.
Rosencrantz and Guildenstern
are heading to England.
I have a lot to tell you about them.
Goodbye.
From your friend, Hamlet."
Come, I'll make way
for your letters...
...and do it quickly
so you can guide me...
...to the person you got them from.
Now your conscience must
clear me of any blame...
...and you must consider me
a friend...
...since you've heard,
and understood...
...that the one who killed your noble father
also tried to kill me.
That's clear. But tell me...
...why didn't you take action
against these serious crimes...
...so terrible and severe,
when your safety...
...wisdom, and everything else
urged you to do so?
Oh, for two specific reasons
that might seem weak to you...
...but are strong to me.
The queen, his mother,
is almost entirely dependent on him.
And for myself—
Whether it's a virtue or a curse,
be it one or the other.
—she is so essential
to my life and soul...
...that, like a star that doesn't move
except in its orbit...
...I couldn't act without her.
The other reason
I couldn't make it public...
...is the great love
the people have for him...
...who, overlooking all his faults
because of their affection...
...would, like a spring
that turns wood to stone...
...turn his chains into blessings...
...so that my efforts,
too weak for such strong opposition...
...would have backfired,
and not hit their target.
And so I've lost a noble father.
A sister driven to desperation...
...whose worth,
if praise could be given again...
...stood as a challenger, on a pedestal...
...of all the age for her virtues.
- But I'll have my revenge.
- Don't lose sleep over that.
You must not think
that we are so dull and lifeless...
...that we can let danger shake us
and think it's fun.
You'll hear more soon.
I loved your father, and we love ourselves.
And that, I hope,
will teach you to imagine—
CLAUDIUS:
What's going on? What's the news?
Letters, my lord, from Hamlet.
This one is for Your Majesty,
and this one is for the queen.
From Hamlet? Who delivered them?
Sailors, my lord, they say.
I didn't see them myself.
Claudio gave them to me.
He got them
from the person who brought them.
CLAUDIUS: Laertes, you should hear them.
Leave us.
"High and mighty, you should know
that I have arrived unexpectedly in your kingdom.
Tomorrow, I will ask permission
to see you in person...
...when I will, first asking your pardon,
explain the reasons...
...for my sudden and strange return.
Hamlet."
What does this mean?
Have all the others come back too?
Or is this some kind of trick, and not true?
- Do you recognize the handwriting?
- It's Hamlet's writing.
"Unexpectedly," and in a postscript here
he says "alone."
- Can you give me advice?
- I'm confused, my lord.
But let him come.
It stirs up the anger in my heart
that I will live to tell him to his face:
"This is how you die."
If that's the case, Laertes—
How could it be otherwise?
—will you follow my lead?
Yes, my lord,
as long as you don't make peace with him.
For your own peace.
If he's returned now,
having stopped his journey...
...and he plans
not to continue it...
...I will lead him into a trap,
which I've already planned...
...where he won't have a choice but to fall.
And for his death...
...no blame will come our way.
Even his mother will think it was an accident
and call it a mishap.
My lord, I'll follow your lead.
Especially if you can plan it
so that I can be the one to do it.
That works perfectly.
You've been talked about
a lot since your travels—
And Hamlet has heard about it.
—for a skill
they say you excel in.
Your overall talents didn't make him
as envious as that one skill did...
...which, in my opinion,
is the least impressive.
- What skill is that, my lord?
- A small accomplishment for the young...
...but important too.
For youth suits
the carefree style it wears...
...just as much as old age suits
its serious and dignified attire.
Two months ago,
there was a gentleman from Normandy here.
I've seen myself,
and fought against, the French...
...and they're good on horseback,
but this guy was like magic.
He seemed to become one with his horse...
...and performed such amazing
feats with it...
...as if he and the horse
were one incredible creature.
He exceeded my expectations so far.
I can't match his skill in deception and tricks.
...I'm not as good as he was.
- Was he a Norman?
- Yes, a Norman.
- I bet it was Lamord.
- Exactly, it was him.
I know him well. He's truly the pride
and jewel of our nation.
He spoke highly of you...
...and praised your skill
in art and defense...
...especially with your sword...
...saying it would be amazing
if anyone could match you.
He swore that their country's fencers
had no skill or awareness...
...if they faced you, sir.
His praise
made Hamlet so envious...
...that all he could do
was wish and beg...
...for you to come quickly
to spar with him.
- So, from this--
- What do you mean by this, my lord?
Laertes, did you truly care for your father?
Or are you just pretending to be sad,
showing emotion without feeling?
Why do you ask?
Not because I doubt
you loved your father...
...but because I know
love changes over time...
...and I've seen, through experience...
...that time dulls its intensity.
Within the very flame of love...
...there's something that can
diminish it.
And nothing stays perfect forever.
For goodness, when it becomes excessive,
destroys itself.
What we intend to do,
we should do when we want to.
Because this intention changes...
...and faces obstacles and delays...
...as numerous as there are people,
actions, and events.
And then this intention
becomes like a wasted sigh...
...that harms by relieving.
But let's get to the heart of the matter.
Hamlet is coming back.
What would you do
to prove you're truly your father's son...
...in actions, not just words?
I'd kill him in a church.
No place should protect a murderer.
Revenge should have no limits.
But, dear Laertes, will you do this?
Stay hidden in your room.
When Hamlet returns, he'll know
that you're back.
We'll have people praise
your skills...
...and enhance the reputation
the Frenchman gave you.
We'll bring you together,
and place bets on you both.
He, being careless, very generous,
and not suspicious...
...won't inspect the swords.
So with ease...
...or a little trickery...
...you can choose a sharp sword...
...and in a practiced move,
get revenge for your father.
I'll do it.
And for that reason,
I'll put poison on my sword.
I bought a deadly poison from a charlatan...
...so lethal that if you just dip a knife in it...
...wherever it cuts,
no remedy so rare...
...made from all the best herbs
with healing powers under the moon...
...can save anyone from dying
if they're just scratched with it.
I'll coat my sword with this poison,
so if I just graze him...
...it could kill him.
Let's think more about this.
Consider what timing
and methods will work best for us.
If this doesn't work...
...and our plan becomes obvious
because we mess up...
...it would be better not to try it.
So this plan should have
a backup or alternative...
...in case the first one fails.
Wait, let me think.
We'll make a formal bet
on your skills...
I've got it.
When you're moving
and you're hot and thirsty—
Make your moves
more intense for that purpose.
—and he asks for a drink...
...I'll have a special cup ready for him,
and if he takes a sip...
...if he somehow escapes
your poisoned strike...
[RUSTLING]
...our plan might still work.
But wait, what's that noise?
What's going on, dear queen?
One tragedy follows another so quickly.
Your sister has drowned...
...Laertes.
Drowned?
Oh no.
Where?
There's a willow
growing at an angle over the brook...
...that shows its white leaves
in the clear stream.
She made whimsical garlands
out of them...
...with crowflowers, nettles,
daisies, and long purples...
...which the rude shepherds
call by a vulgar name...
...but our modest girls
call them dead men's fingers.
There on the hanging branches...
...while trying to hang her garlands,
a jealous branch broke...
...and down fell her garlands
and she herself into the crying brook.
Her clothes spread wide...
...and like a mermaid
they kept her afloat for a while.
During that time she sang
bits of old songs...
...as if unaware of her own danger...
...or like a creature native to
and comfortable in the water.
But it couldn't last long...
...before her clothes,
heavy with water...
...dragged the poor soul
from her beautiful song to a muddy death.
Oh no, so she drowned.
Drowned.
You've had too much water,
poor Ophelia...
...so I won't cry.
But still, it's our habit.
Nature follows its course.
Let shame say what it wants.
[SOBBING]
When these tears are gone,
I'll be done grieving.
Goodbye, my lord.
I have a fiery speech
that wants to burn bright...
...but this foolishness puts it out.
Let's go, Gertrude.
I worked hard to calm him down.
Now I'm afraid this will set him off again.
So...
...let's go.
Is she to be buried in a Christian way
when she took her own life?
I'm telling you she is,
so dig her grave right away.
The coroner has ruled on it,
and says it's a Christian burial.
How can that be unless she drowned herself
to save herself?
Well, that's what they decided.
It must be self-defense,
there's no other way.
Here's the point:
If I knowingly drown myself,
it's an act.
And an act has three parts:
to act, to do, and to perform.
So, she knowingly drowned herself.
- But listen, Goodman Delver.
- Give me a moment.
Here's the water. Got it?
Here's the man. Got it.
If the man goes to the water
and drowns himself...
...he goes, whether he wants to or not.
Remember that.
But if the water comes to him
and drowns him, he didn't drown himself.
So, if he's not responsible for his own death,
he doesn't shorten his own life.
- But is this the law?
- Yes, indeed: coroner's inquest law.
Want to know the truth?
If she hadn't been a lady...
...she would have been buried
outside of Christian grounds.
You're right,
and it's a shame...
...that important people have
privileges in this world...
...to drown or hang themselves
more than ordinary people.
Come on, my shovel.
The only true gentlemen
are gardeners, ditch diggers, and gravediggers.
- They uphold Adam's profession.
- Was he a gentleman?
- He was the first to bear arms.
- He didn't have any.
What, are you a heathen?
How do you understand the Bible?
The Bible says Adam dug.
Could he dig without arms?
I'll ask you another question.
If you don't answer me properly,
just admit it.
- Go on.
- Who builds something stronger...
...than a mason,
a shipbuilder, or a carpenter?
The gallows-maker.
Because that structure
lasts longer than a thousand tenants.
[BOTH LAUGHING]
I really like your wit, honestly.
The gallows is quite effective.
But how is it effective?
It's effective for those who do wrong.
Now, you're wrong to say the gallows
is built stronger than the church.
So, the gallows might be useful for you.
Try again, come on.
"Who builds stronger than a mason,
a shipbuilder, or a carpenter?"
- Tell me that, and take a break.
- Well, I can tell you.
Go ahead.
Actually, I can't tell you.
Don't strain your brain over it...
...because your slow mind
won't get any faster by forcing it.
And when you're asked this question next,
say "a grave-maker."
The houses he builds
last until the end of time.
Go, get yourself to Yaughan.
Bring me a drink.
[GULPING]
[GRAVEDIGGER SIGHS]
[SINGING]
When I was young and in love
Oh, I thought it was so sweet
GRAVEDIGGER:
To shorten the time for my benefit
Oh, I thought there was nothing better
Doesn't this guy realize what he's doing
that he sings while digging graves?
It's become second nature to him
to do it easily.
HAMLET:
That's true.
Those with little work
have a more delicate sense.
GRAVEDIGGER:
But age, with its sneaky steps
Has caught up with me
And sent me to the land
As if I had never been like this
That skull once had a tongue
and could sing.
How he throws it to the ground
as if it were Cain's jawbone...
...that did the first murder.
This could be the skull of a politician
which this fool now surpasses...
...one who thought they could outsmart God,
couldn't it?
- It could be, my lord.
- Or of a courtier, who could say:
"Good morning, sweet lord.
How are you, sweet lord?"
HAMLET: This could be my Lord Such-a-one,
who praised my Lord Such-a-one's horse...
...when he wanted to borrow it, couldn't it?
Yes, my lord.
Why, indeed,
and now my Lady Worm's...
[GRAVEDIGGER WHISTLING
AND HUMMING]
...jawless, and knocked
around the head with a gravedigger's spade.
Here's a fine change,
if only we could see it.
Did these bones cost no more to create
than to play games with them?
Just thinking about it makes me ache.
HAMLET:
Oh, there's another one.
Why couldn't that be the skull
of a lawyer?
Where are his clever arguments now, his tricks,
his cases, his property, and his schemes?
HAMLET: Why does he allow
this rude guy now...
...to hit him on the head
with a dirty shovel...
...and not tell him
about his legal rights? Hmm?
This guy might have been in his time
a big land buyer...
...with his laws,
his acknowledgments, his fines...
...his double deals, his recoveries.
Is this the end of his wealth
and the result of his recoveries...
...to have his fine head full of dirt?
Will his legal documents
not guarantee him more of his purchases...
...and double ones too, than the size
of a piece of paper?
The very deeds of his land
will barely fit in this box...
...and must the owner himself
have no more, huh?
Not a bit more, my lord.
Isn't parchment made from sheepskins?
Yes, my lord, and from calfskins too.
They are sheep and calves
who seek assurance in that.
HAMLET:
I will talk to this guy.
- Whose grave is this, sir?
- Mine, sir.
[SINGING]
Oh, a pit of clay to be made
For such a guest is fitting
I think it's yours, since you're lying in it.
You're lying about it, sir,
so it's not yours.
For my part, I don't lie in it,
and yet it is mine.
You do lie in it,
to be in it and say it's yours.
It's for the dead, not for the living,
so you're lying.
It's a quick lie, sir,
it'll come back from me to you.
- Who are you digging it for?
- For no man, sir.
- For what woman, then?
- For no one, either.
Who is going to be buried in it?
Someone who was a woman, sir,
but God rest her soul, she's dead.
How straightforward this guy is.
We must speak clearly,
or confusion will get us.
By the Lord, Horatio, for the past three years
I've noticed it.
Times have changed so much
that the peasant's toe...
...comes so close to the courtier's heel
it rubs his sore spot.
How long have you been a gravedigger?
Of all the days in the year,
I started on the day...
...that our last king, Hamlet,
defeated Fortinbras.
- How long ago was that?
- Can't you tell that?
Any fool can tell that.
It was the very day
that young Hamlet was born.
The one who went mad and was sent to England.
Yes, indeed, why was he sent
to England?
Well, because he was mad.
He'll recover his sanity there,
or if he doesn't, it won't matter much there.
- Why?
- It won't be noticeable in him there.
The men there are just as crazy as he is.
[HORATIO CHUCKLES]
- How did he go mad?
- Very strangely, they say.
- How strangely?
- Honestly, just by losing his mind.
- On what basis?
- Well, here in Denmark.
[HAMLET GROANS]
I've been the sexton here,
since I was a boy, for 30 years.
How long will a man lie
in the ground before he rots?
Honestly, if he's not rotten before he dies—
As we have many diseased bodies these days
that barely hold together when buried.
—he'll last you
about eight or nine years.
- A tanner will last you nine years.
- Why him more than others?
Well, sir, his skin
is so tanned from his work...
...that it keeps out water
for a long time...
...and water is a serious decayer
of a dead body.
Here's a skull, sir, now.
This skull has been in the ground
for twenty-three years.
- Whose was it?
- It belonged to a mad fellow.
- Whose do you think it was?
- No, I don't know.
Oh, a curse
on him for being a mad rogue.
He once poured a jug of wine
on my head.
This very skull, sir,
was Yorick's, the king's jester.
- This one?
- Yes, that one.
Let me see.
Alas...
...poor Yorick.
I knew him, Horatio.
A guy full of jokes,
with a great imagination.
He carried me on his back
a thousand times.
HAMLET: And now, how horrible
it is in my mind.
It makes me sick.
Here were the lips that I kissed
I don't know how many times.
Where are your jokes now...
...your pranks, your songs,
your bursts of laughter...
...that used
to make everyone laugh?
Not one left to mock your own smile?
Completely fallen?
Now, go to my lady's room...
...tell her, even if she puts on thick makeup,
she will end up like this.
HAMLET:
Make her laugh at that.
- Please, Horatio, tell me one thing.
- What's that, my lord?
Do you think Alexander looked
like this in the ground?
Just like that.
And smelled like this? Pfft.
Just like that, my lord.
To what lowly uses
we might return, Horatio.
Why can't imagination
follow the noble dust of Alexander...
...until it finds it stopping a hole?
It would be overthinking
to think like that.
No, honestly, not at all, just to follow him
there with enough modesty...
...and a good chance to lead it, like this.
HAMLET:
Alexander died, Alexander was buried.
Alexander turned to dust,
and dust is earth...
...we make clay from earth,
and why from that clay...
...that he became,
couldn't they stop a beer barrel?
HAMLET: Powerful Caesar,
dead and turned to clay...
...might plug a hole
to keep the wind out.
Oh, that the earth...
...which kept the world in awe...
...should patch a wall
to keep out the winter's cold.
[BIRD SCREECHING
AND THEN RUSTLING]
HAMLET:
Wait a moment.
Wait a moment, step aside.
Here comes the king,
the queen, and the courtiers.
HAMLET: Who are they following,
and with such incomplete rites?
This suggests the body they follow
took its own life.
HAMLET:
It was someone of status.
Let's lie low for a bit and watch.
What other ceremony is there?
That's Laertes, a very noble young man.
Watch.
What other ceremony is there?
Her funeral rites have been extended
as much as we are allowed.
Her death was uncertain...
...and if not for the king's command
overruling the rules...
...she would have been buried in unholy ground
until Judgment Day.
For prayers, shards, flints,
and pebbles should have been thrown on her.
Yet here she has her virgin rites,
her maiden flowers...
...and the ringing of the bell
and burial.
Is there nothing more to be done?
Nothing more to be done.
PRIEST: We would disrespect
the service for the dead...
...to sing a solemn requiem and give her
the same rest as those who died in peace.
Lay her in the earth.
And from her pure and untainted body
may violets grow.
I tell you, rude priest...
...my sister will be an angel
when you're howling in hell.
What?
Sweet Ophelia.
GERTRUDE:
Sweets for the sweet.
Goodbye.
I hoped you would have been
my Hamlet's wife.
I thought I would have decorated your bridal bed,
sweet girl...
...and not scattered flowers on your grave.
Oh, triple sorrow...
...fall ten times over
on that cursed head...
...whose evil act
took away your brilliant mind...
...from you.
[SHOUTS]
Hold off the earth for a moment...
...until I have held her once more
in my arms.
Now heap your dust
on the living and the dead...
...until you've turned this flat land into a mountain
taller than old Pelion...
...or the towering peak of blue Olympus!
HAMLET: Who is this person whose grief
is so intense...
...whose words of sorrow
call upon the wandering stars...
...and make them stand still
like amazed listeners?
It's me, Hamlet the Dane!
The devil take your soul.
[GRUNTING]
You're not praying well.
Please take your hands off my throat...
...because even though
I'm not quick-tempered and impulsive...
...I do have something in me
that you should be careful of.
- Let go of him.
- Pull them apart.
Hamlet, Hamlet!
Please, my lord, calm down.
I'll fight him over this
until I can't keep my eyes open.
Oh my son, what is it about?
I loved Ophelia.
Forty thousand brothers couldn't,
with all their love...
...match mine.
- What will you do for her?
- Oh, he's gone mad, Laertes.
For God's sake, leave him alone.
Damn it, show me what you'll do.
Will you cry, will you fight, huh...
...will you fast, will you hurt yourself,
will you drink vinegar, eat a crocodile?
I'll do it.
Did you come here to whine,
to outdo me by jumping into her grave?
Be buried alive with her, and I will too.
And if you talk about mountains...
...let them throw
millions of acres on us, until the ground...
...burns his head
against the scorching sun...
...making Ossa look tiny.
No, if you're going to rant,
I'll rant just as well as you.
This is just madness...
...and for a while
it will take hold of him.
Soon, as calm as a dove...
...when her golden eggs
hatch, he'll sit quietly.
Listen, sir.
HAMLET:
Why are you treating me like this?
I always loved you.
But it doesn't matter.
Even if Hercules tries his best...
...the cat will still meow...
...and the dog will have his day.
Please, Horatio, stay with him.
[WHISPERING] Remember our talk last night.
Be patient.
We'll deal with this right away.
CLAUDIUS:
Good Gertrude...
...keep an eye on your son.
This grave will have a living memorial.
We'll soon have a moment of peace.
Until then, let's proceed with patience.
That's enough about this, sir.
Now you'll see the other part.
- Do you remember all the details?
- I remember them, my lord.
Sir, I had a kind of internal struggle
that kept me from sleeping.
I thought I was lying
worse than prisoners in chains.
Recklessly, and thank goodness for recklessness...
...we sometimes find that our mistakes
actually help us...
...when our well-thought-out plans fail...
...and we should learn
there's a higher power guiding our outcomes.
- No matter how rough our attempts are.
- That's definitely true.
I got up from my cabin, my robe
wrapped around me in the dark...
...I fumbled to find them, got what I wanted,
handled their documents...
...and finally went back
to my own room...
...boldly,
my fears making me forget my manners...
...to open their important orders,
where I found, Horatio--
Oh, what royal trickery.
--a precise command,
filled with all sorts of reasons...
...claiming it was for Denmark's well-being
and England's too, with urgency!
Such threats and horrors in my life,
that upon reading it, without any delay...
...not even time to sharpen the ax...
- ...my head was to be cut off.
- Is that possible?
Here's the order,
read it when you have more time.
- But do you want to hear how I handled it?
- Please, tell me.
Being surrounded
by such treachery--
Before I could even think...
...my mind was already at work.
--I sat down,
created a new order, wrote it neatly.
Ha, I used to think, like many officials do...
...that writing neatly was beneath me and tried hard
to forget that skill.
But, sir, now it was very useful to me.
- Do you want to know what I wrote?
- Yes, please.
A strong request from the king...
...since England was his loyal ally...
...as their friendship
might thrive like a palm tree...
...as peace should always
wear its wheat garland...
...and stand as a link
between their friendships...
...and many similar reasons
of great importance...
...that upon reading
and understanding these contents...
...without any further discussion
more or less...
...he should have those messengers
put to immediate death.
- Without even time for confession.
- How was this sealed?
Well, even in that, heaven was on my side.
I had my father's ring in my purse...
...which was a copy
of the Danish seal.
I folded the document
like the original...
...signed it, stamped it,
and placed it securely...
...the switch never discovered, ha.
The next day, we had our sea battle.
What happened after that
you already know.
So...
...Guildenstern and Rosencrantz are going to die.
You know, they were eager
to take on this job.
I don't feel guilty about them.
Their downfall
is because of their own actions.
It's dangerous
when someone of lower status gets...
...caught between the fierce conflicts
of powerful enemies.
What kind of king is this?
Don't you think
it's my duty now—
The one who killed my father
and seduced my mother...
...interfered with my chances
and my ambitions...
...tried to take my life,
and with such deceit.
Isn't it the right thing
to take him down myself?
And wouldn't it be wrong...
...to let this corrupt person
cause more harm?
He'll soon find out
from England...
...what happened with that situation.
It won't take long.
In the meantime, I have control...
...and a man's life...
...is as easy to end as saying "one."
But I'm really sorry, dear Horatio,
that I lost my cool with Laertes.
Because in his situation,
I see a reflection of my own.
I'll try to make peace with him.
[SIGHS]
But honestly, his intense grief
really got me worked up.
Quiet, who's coming?
Welcome back
to Denmark, my lord.
I sincerely thank you, sir.
HAMLET: Do you know this annoying guy?
HORATIO: No, my lord.
You're better off not knowing him,
because it's a flaw to be acquainted with him.
He owns a lot of land, and it's fertile.
Even if a beast rules over other beasts,
his place will be at the king's table.
He's a fool, but as I said,
he owns a lot of worthless land.
OSRIC:
Dear lord...
...if you have a moment, I have something
to tell you from the King.
I'll hear it, sir,
with full attention.
Uh, wear your hat properly.
It's meant for your head.
I appreciate it, but it's very hot.
No, it's quite cold. The wind is from the north.
It is a bit cold, my lord, indeed.
But I still think it's very humid
and hot for my taste.
Yes, extremely, my lord.
It's very humid, like—
I can't quite describe it, ha-ha.
But, my lord, the King asked me
to inform you...
...that he has placed a big bet
on you.
OSRIC: Sir, here's the situation.
- Please, remember this.
No, really, my lord,
for my comfort, honestly.
Sir, Laertes has just arrived at court.
Believe me, he's a true gentleman...
...with many admirable qualities,
very sociable and impressive.
Honestly, to speak sincerely about him,
he is the standard or example of nobility.
Because you'll find in him the essence
of what a gentleman should be.
Sir, describing him
loses nothing in your words.
HAMLET: Even though I know
listing his qualities one by one...
...would overwhelm the memory
and not compare to his quick wit.
In truth,
I consider him to be a person of great importance...
...and his mix of scarcity and uniqueness,
to describe him accurately...
...he is his own reflection...
...and anyone who tries to follow him,
would only be his shadow, nothing more.
Your lordship speaks
very accurately about him.
What's the point, sir?
Why are we discussing the gentleman...
- ...with such unrefined words?
- Sir?
Isn't it possible to understand
in another language?
You will, sir, truly.
What's the purpose of mentioning
this gentleman?
- Laertes?
- His wallet is already empty.
All his fine words are used up.
- About him, sir.
- I know you're not unaware--
I wish you were. But honestly, if you were,
it wouldn't help me much. Well?
You are aware
of how excellent Laertes is.
I dare not admit that,
in case I compare myself to him in excellence.
But to truly know a man
is to know oneself.
I mean, sir, in terms of his skill.
But in the reputation given to him by others,
in his reward, he's unmatched.
- What's his weapon?
- Sword and dagger.
- Those are two of his weapons. But okay.
- Ha.
The king, sir, has bet
six Barbary horses with him...
- ...against which he has wagered--
- Wagered?
--as I understand, six French swords
and daggers...
...with their accessories,
like belts, hangers, and so on.
Three of the accessories, honestly,
are quite fancy...
...very fitting to the handles...
...very elegant accessories,
and quite imaginative.
What do you call the accessories?
I knew you needed clarification
before you were done.
The accessories, sir, are the hangers.
The term would be more appropriate
if we could carry cannons at our sides.
- I wish they could be hangers until then.
- Ah, ha!
But moving on: six Barbary horses
against six French swords...
...their accessories,
and three imaginative...
- Accessories.
- ...accessories.
That's the French bet against the Danish.
Why is this "wagered," as you call it?
The king, sir, has bet, sir, that
in a dozen rounds between you and him...
...he won't beat you by more than three hits.
He has bet on 12 for nine.
And it would be tested immediately...
...if your lordship
would agree to it.
What if I say no?
I mean, my lord,
the challenge of your participation in the test.
Sir, I'll walk here in the hall.
If it pleases His Majesty,
this is my usual time for a break.
Bring the foils.
If the gentleman is willing,
and the king sticks to his plan...
...I'll win for him if I can.
If not, I'll only gain my shame
and a few hits.
- Should I deliver your message like this?
- Yes, to this effect, sir.
In whatever style suits you.
I send my respects to your lordship.
Yours truly.
HAMLET:
Um....
He praises himself well,
since no one else will.
This young bird runs off
with the eggshell still on his head.
He was agreeable with his nurse
before he even drank her milk.
That's how he is—like many others
that this foolish age admires.
They've only learned the current trends
and the outward manners of meeting...
...a sort of superficial collection...
...that carries them through
the most popular opinions...
...and if you test them,
they burst like bubbles.
My lord.
His Majesty sent a message to you
through young Osric...
...who reports back to him,
that you will meet him in the hall.
He wants to know if you're still willing
to play with Laertes...
- ...or if you need more time.
- I'm committed to my plans.
They follow the king's wishes:
If he's ready, so am I.
Now or whenever,
as long as I'm as capable as I am now.
The king and queen and everyone
are coming down.
Just in time.
The queen wants you
to be friendly with Laertes...
...before you start playing.
She's given me good instructions.
You'll lose this bet, my lord.
I don't think so.
Since he went to France,
I've been practicing continuously.
I'll win with the odds.
But you wouldn't believe
how uneasy I feel inside.
[SIGHS]
But it doesn't matter.
No, my good lord.
HAMLET:
It's just foolishness.
But it's the kind of doubt
that might trouble a woman.
If you feel uneasy, listen to it.
I'll stop them from coming here,
and say you're not ready.
Not at all.
We reject predictions.
There's a special fate
even in a sparrow's fall.
If it's meant to happen now, it won't be later.
If it won't happen later, it will be now.
If it's not now...
...it will happen eventually.
Being prepared is everything.
Since no one knows anything
about what they leave behind...
...why worry about leaving early?
Let it be.
Come on, Hamlet, come here,
and take this hand from me.
Please forgive me, sir.
I've wronged you.
But forgive me as a gentleman would.
HAMLET: Everyone here knows,
and you must have heard...
...how I'm troubled
by a severe distraction.
What I've done that might have upset
your nature, honor, and expectations...
...I declare was madness.
Was it Hamlet who wronged Laertes?
Never Hamlet.
If Hamlet is taken away from himself, and
when he's not himself, he wrongs Laertes...
...then it's not Hamlet doing it,
Hamlet denies it.
Who does it, then?
His madness.
If that's the case, Hamlet is on the side
that's been wronged.
His madness is poor Hamlet's enemy.
HAMLET: Sir, in front of everyone here,
let me say that I didn't intend any harm...
...and free me in your generous thoughts...
...so much that it's like I shot an arrow
over the house...
...and accidentally hurt my brother.
I am satisfied in my heart...
...which should motivate me
most to get revenge.
But when it comes to honor...
...I stand apart,
and won't reconcile...
...until some respected elders
of known honor...
...give me a reason and precedent for peace
to keep my reputation intact.
But until then,
I accept your offered friendship like love...
...and won't wrong it.
I accept it freely...
...and will play this friendly match
openly.
HAMLET:
Give us the swords. Let's go.
- Give me one.
- I'll be your opponent, Laertes.
In my ignorance, your skill will,
like a star in the darkest night...
...shine brightly.
- You're mocking me, sir.
- No, I swear.
Give them the swords, young Osric.
CLAUDIUS:
Cousin Hamlet, do you know the bet?
Yes, my lord. You've placed the odds
on the weaker side.
CLAUDIUS:
I'm not worried. I've seen you both.
But since he's improved,
we have the odds.
This one's too heavy.
Let me try another.
This one feels right.
Are all these swords the same length?
Yes, my lord.
Set the wine cups
on that table.
If Hamlet gets the first or second hit,
or answers the third exchange...
...let all the cannons
fire from the battlements.
The king will drink
to Hamlet's continued success...
...and into the cup
he will toss a union...
...more valuable than that
which four consecutive kings...
...have worn in Denmark's crown.
CLAUDIUS:
Give me the cup...
...and let the kettle speak to the trumpet,
the trumpet to the cannoneer outside...
...the cannons to the heavens,
the heavens to the earth:
"Now the king drinks to Hamlet."
Come on, start.
And you, the judges...
...keep a careful watch.
- Let's go, sir.
- Come on, my lord.
[GRUNTING]
[GERTRUDE GASPS]
HAMLET: One!
- No!
Judgment!
A hit, a very clear hit.
LAERTES: Well, again.
- Wait. Give me a drink.
Hamlet, this pearl is yours.
Here's to your health.
- Give him the cup.
- I'll play this round first.
Set it aside for a bit.
[GRUNTING]
HAMLET:
Come on.
[GRUNTING]
Yes.
[LAERTES ROARS]
[LAERTES YELLS]
[CROWD MUMBLING]
[LAERTES SHOUTING]
Another hit. What do you say?
A touch, a touch, I admit it.
[CROWD CHEERS]
Our son will win.
He's out of shape and short of breath.
Here, Hamlet, take my napkin.
Wipe your forehead.
The queen drinks
to your success, Hamlet.
Thank you, madam.
[SHOUTS]
Gertrude!
Don't drink.
[GERTRUDE LAUGHS]
I will, my lord. Please, forgive me.
CLAUDIUS:
It's the poisoned cup.
It's too late.
I can't drink yet, madam. Soon.
Come, let me wipe your face.
My lord, I'll hit him now.
I don't think so.
And yet it's almost
against my conscience.
Attack--!
[GUARD GRUNTS]
Come for the third round, Laertes,
you're just stalling.
Please, give it your best shot.
I'm worried you're making a fool of me.
[LAUGHTER]
Is that so?
Let's go.
LAERTES:
Here I come.
[HAMLET GRUNTS]
[HAMLET ROARING
AND THEN CROWD MURMURING]
[GRUNTING]
- Nothing either way.
- Separate them, they're angry.
No, come back!
Look at the queen there, hey!
HORATIO:
They're both bleeding.
[LAERTES SHOUTS
AND THEN SCREAMS]
[LAERTES GASPING]
How are you, Laertes?
Like a bird caught in my own trap, Osric.
I got what I deserved
from my own betrayal.
[HAMLET PANTING]
How's the queen?
She fainted seeing them bleed.
GERTRUDE:
No, no...
...it's the drink.
GERTRUDE:
The drink.
Oh my dear Hamlet.
The drink, the drink.
I've been poisoned.
Villainy.
Lock the doors!
- Treachery! Find out who did it!
- It's here, Hamlet.
LAERTES:
Hamlet, you're dying.
No medicine in the world
can help you now.
You have less than half an hour to live.
The deadly weapon
is in your hand...
...sharp and poisoned.
The evil plan
has backfired on me.
LAERTES:
Look, here I lie, never to get up again.
Your mother's poisoned.
I can't go on.
[CHOKING]
The king...
...the king's at fault.
Treason!
[THUD AND THEN OSRIC GROANS]
The tip is poisoned too?
Then, poison, do your job.
Unh! Oh, help me, friends.
I'm only hurt.
[CLAUDIUS SCREAMING]
[CLAUDIUS GRUNTING
AND THEN GAGGING]
Here, you incestuous, murderous,
damned Dane...
...drink this potion.
Is your union here? Follow my mother.
He got what he deserved.
It's a poison he made himself.
Forgive me,
noble Hamlet.
My death and my father's
aren't your fault...
...and yours isn't mine.
May heaven free you from it.
I'm coming with you.
I'm dying, Horatio.
[HAMLET GROANING]
Goodbye, wretched queen.
You who look pale and tremble
at this event...
...who are just silent witnesses
to this act...
...if I only had time--
But Death, that strict officer,
won't wait.
--Oh, I could tell you.
But never mind.
Horatio, I'm dying, but you're alive.
Tell my story
to those who don't know.
Don't believe it.
I'm more like an ancient Roman
than a Dane.
There's still some drink left.
As a man,
give me the cup. Let go!
By heaven!
I'll have it.
HAMLET:
Oh God, Horatio...
[CUP CLATTERS]
...what a damaged reputation...
...with things left unknown
will remain after me.
If you ever cared for me...
...stay away from happiness for a bit.
HAMLET:
And in this harsh world...
...breathe painfully
to tell my story.
[CANNONS FIRING]
What's that warlike noise?
Young Fortinbras, returning victorious
from Poland...
...is giving this warlike salute
to the English ambassadors.
I'm dying, Horatio.
The strong poison
overpowers my spirit.
I can't live
to hear the news from England...
...but I predict...
...the election will favor Fortinbras.
[GRUNTING]
He has my dying support.
So tell him...
...with all the events, big and small...
...that have happened.
The rest...
...is...
...silence.
Now a noble heart breaks.
Good night...
...sweet prince...
...and may angels guide you
to your rest.
[DRUMS BEATING]
HORATIO:
Why is the drum coming here?
FORTINBRAS:
Where is this scene?
HORATIO:
What are you looking for?
If it's sorrow or amazement...
...stop searching.
This scene screams chaos.
FORTINBRAS:
Oh, proud death...
...what feast are you preparing
in your eternal realm...
...that you've struck down so many princes
so violently?
[DOOR OPENS]
AMBASSADOR:
The sight is grim...
...and our news from England
comes too late.
The ears that should hear us
are now deaf...
...to tell him his orders
are completed...
...that Rosencrantz and Guildenstern...
...are dead.
Where do we get our thanks?
Not from his mouth...
...even if he were alive to thank you.
He never ordered
their deaths.
But since...
...we've stumbled upon this bloody issue...
...you from the Polish wars...
...and you from England,
are here now...
...arrange for these bodies...
...to be displayed on a high stage.
HORATIO:
And let me speak...
...to the world that doesn't know yet
how these things happened.
HORATIO:
So you'll hear...
...of lustful...
...bloody...
...and unnatural deeds...
...of accidental judgments...
...random killings...
...of deaths caused by clever
and forced reasons.
And in the end...
...plans gone wrong
backfire on the planners.
All this...
...I can truthfully tell.
Let's hurry to hear it...
...and call the noblest to listen.
FORTINBRAS:
As for me...
...I accept my fate with sadness.
I have some rightful claims
in this kingdom...
...which now invite me
to take advantage.
About that...
...I will also have reason to speak...
...and from his mouth
whose voice will call for more.
But let this same
be done right away...
...even while people are still in shock...
...to prevent more accidents
from plots and mistakes happening.
Let four captains carry Hamlet,
like a soldier, to the stage...
...because he would have likely,
proven to be very noble.
FORTINBRAS: And for his farewell,
the soldiers' music and war honors...
...speak highly of him.
Take the body away.
A sight like this belongs on the battlefield...
...but here it seems very wrong.
Go.
Tell the soldiers to fire a salute.